<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon Mijn Heer Fagels letter concerning our penal laws and tests with remarks upon that subject, occasioned by the publishing of that letter.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3204</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16317744</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16317744</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105289</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25451)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105289)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1604:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon Mijn Heer Fagels letter concerning our penal laws and tests with remarks upon that subject, occasioned by the publishing of that letter.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 [i.e. 26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Allowed to be publish'd this 13th day of July 1688."</note>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" addressed to William Penn Esq.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fagel, Gaspar, 1634-1688.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  England.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105289:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105289:1"/>
            <p>Animadverſions UPON <hi>Mijn Heer Fagels Letter</hi> CONCERNING OUR PENAL LAWS AND TESTS; WITH REMARKS Upon that SUBJECT. <hi>Occaſioned by the Publiſhing of that</hi> LETTER.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Allowed to be Publiſh'd</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 13th <hi>Day of</hi> July 1688.</date>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin</hi> at the <hi>Two Swans</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſgate.</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105289:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105289:2"/>
            <head>TO William Penn <hi>Eſq</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BY theſe Papers which I ſend to be Peruſed by you, my Worthy Friend, you may perceive I have (as you deſired me) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the Contens of <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi>'s. Letter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> and Remarkt upon that Subject, as Occaſion was offered.</p>
            <p>Before I had finiſhed what I intended therein, The Solution of the Popular Objection againſt the Repeal of the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> was Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Therein the Task you impoſed upon me, was ſo effectually Perform'd by the Author, that you may well demand a Reaſon, why I did not upon ſight of it deſiſt from any farther proceeding upon this Subject.</p>
            <p>My Apology is, Tho that has Subſtantially pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented me, you did not formally forbid me.</p>
            <p>The Arguments of it are ſufficient to fortifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Fears Suggeſted from future Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if Foundations be well laid in the next, for Liberty of Conſcience; and may ſerve (as is hinted in the Title Page) for an Anſwer to this Letter of <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel,</hi> as well as to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Papers Publiſhed upon this Subject. But yet I perceive there are, who adhere to the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Vogue—That we are more ſecure in our Religion and Liberties under our preſent Laws for Oaths and Teſts, then we can be by any other Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, if theſe be Repealed: And they ſtrengthen themſelves herein, by what has, been declared by this Letter of <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi> to Mr. <hi>James Stewart;</hi> and becauſe the Author of that Paper does not ſtile it an Anſwer thereto in particular, it ſtill remains with ſome, as if it were unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            <p>I encline to think (and ſhall ſo do till I am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe convinced) No man will attempt openly to Relpy upon thoſe Arguments; But I cannot take Silence in this caſe to be a ſufficient Evidence of a Conviction; I have therefore ſteered another courſe to break this Silence, by offering ſome things to be conſidered upon the ſubject matter of <hi>Mijn Heer Fagel</hi>'s, Letter, as a Moot Caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether contrary to their Highneſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Opinion, many Chriſtians are not ſubject to be very ill uſed, becauſe they differ from the Publick Eſtabliſhed Religion, if theſe Teſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without any further Proviſion by a New Law to ſecure them from ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether thoſe Penal Laws and Teſts are Effectual to Exclude <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> from any ſhare in the Government, Publick Truſts, or Employments; Or whether they have not been improved to a damage, rather then to any real advantage to the Reformed Religion?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether Better, more Juſtifiable, and Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Security, both for our Religion and Civil Rights, may not be obtained if His Majesty pleaſe to give His Royal Aſſent, by Eſtabliſhing the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral matters propoſed in His Declaration for Indulgence, and ſome other Proviſions to be made by a New Law, then can be had or expected by continuing the Penal Laws and Tests as now they are?</p>
            <p>What I have written, tends to reſolve theſe points for a Repeal of our Penal Laws and Tests, If it meet not with better Arguments to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary then hither to have been publiſhed. I have been the more large upon this Subject, becauſe I am of Opinion, (1) That no man can for the cauſe of Religion plead any juſtifiable excuſe for his not rendring Subjection to ſuch as are his Superiours in a Natural or Civil Station, in their lawful Commands. (2) That the inflicting Temporal Penalties for ſuch Errors in Religious Opinions as cannot be Evinc'd by the Principles of Reaſon and Conſcience, to be againſt the common Light of Nature (tho they may be proved by Scripture to be againſt ſuch myſterious Truths as are proper only to the Chriſtian Religion) is not to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied either by the general Law of Nature, or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rules of Scripture. (3) Though the point of Liberty of Conſcience ſeems to be, yet I doubt it is not really granted, but ſtands in ſome need to be more fully inculcated, That each perſon who deſires for himſelf to be free, and not coerced by Penal Laws to Worſhip God contrary to his Conſcience, may be diſpoſed to allow the like Liberty to every other Perſon who deſires it, and is of years of diſcretion to plead for it pon the like terms.</p>
            <p>It is a true ſaying, <hi>Id verum quod Prius;</hi> Truth's Elder than Error: But Error has trod upon the Heels of Truth, by Satan's Transforming
<pb facs="tcp:105289:3"/>himſelf into an Angel of Light, and his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters being Transformed into Miniſters of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; ſo as that the moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, from the firſt Creation of Man upon the Earth, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſucceeding Generations, have been ſo liable to Temptations, as not always to conſider by what Spirit they are Acted—After the Fall of Man, from that Original State of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was at firſt Created, Though Internal Grace, through Faith of the Operation of the Spirit of Chriſt, for the Hope of Redemption by the <hi>Promiſed Seed,</hi> first directed the proper uſe of Religious External Forms, ſo as to render the Worſhippers acceptable therein to God; and in that Reſpect, Liberty of Conſcience had the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency of Perſecution for Conſcience: Yet through the Inſtigation of that <hi>Old Serpent,</hi> (the Spirit of <hi>Antichriſt</hi>) Perſecution for Conſcience, is as old as the Murther of <hi>Abel.</hi> The Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs without the Power, (which then began to ſhew it ſelf in <hi>Cain,</hi> who was of that Wicked one, and ſlew his Brother) has ever ſince manifeſted it ſelf in various Forms, like the Harlot in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 5.6. Gal. 4.29.</note> whoſe Ways are moveable, throughout all Ages in the World.</p>
            <p>And this evil Perſecuting <hi>Spirit</hi> crept, and ſtill inſinuates it ſelf into the viſible Church; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch among them, as have a Zeal for God, and for an outſide Form of Godlineſs, but not according to Knowledge. And this is ſo much the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, becauſe, although the Tract of Holy Scriptures diſcovers, and often repeats the doleful Effects of this (formal, pretended Godly Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of an Erroneous, but really cruel) Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Conſcience;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen 4.8. Mat. 23.35. 1</hi> John <hi>3.11, 12, 13. Jude, verſe 11.</hi>
               </note> and has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved upon Record, from the Beginning to the Concluſion of Holy Writ, the very Name of the firſt Bloody Tranſgreſſor of this ſort, often Repeated, that it might be rendred odious to all future Ages, eſpecially under the Goſpel: Tet how oft has it hapned, (to the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Divine Original, and Verity of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Propheſies) that even ſuch as read them, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, but do not attend to be guided by their Voice, have fulfilled them in Condemning the Juſt? And whilſt they ſpeak, as in the Language of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they <hi>built the Tombs,</hi> and <hi>Garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Sepulchres of the Righteous;</hi> (if they had lived in their Fathers Days, they would not have been Partakers with them in the Blood of the Prophets,) even in the interim, are ſtupidly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of the temper of their own Minds, then bent upon, and in the next Opportunity, actually Perſecuting the Righteous, ſo as to fill up the Meaſure of their Fathers, and bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Blood of all the Prophets, which was ſhed from the Foundation of the World.</hi> My Inducement to touch upon theſe Points, is the Hopes I have conceived, that by His Majeſty's Royal Countenance and Authority, the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Instruments of this Inhumane Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Spirit may be taken out of the Way; ſo as that, although the Malignity of it be as inou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as that of <hi>Babylon,</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 51.7; 8, 9. Mic. 3.3, 4.5.</note> yet its Rage ſhall be ſo fettered as no more to take away Peace from the Earth; whereto the ſetling, and bounding of Religious and Civil Intereſts, upon, and within their diſtinct proper Foundations and Limits, will greatly Contribute.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſay, as it is reported you have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſaid, That if you thought, what you adviſed and perſwaded to, were not the ſafeſt way, you would reckon your ſelves concerned to Act another Part: But I can freely ſay, If I were not of that Mind, I would have choſen to be ſilent, and Acted no Part at all. But being perſwaded, that the modeſt Handling, throughly Penetrating, and free Debating theſe Points, may produce ſuch a Settlement amongſt us, as is moſt juſt and equal; and in that Reſpect, if it be once well laid, moſt likely to remain unſhaken to Perpetuity.</p>
            <p>I have therefore written with an Intent, that what I write ſhould be throughly Scann'd, with a Preparation of mind, to bear the Cenſures of ſuch as have a better diſcerning, and will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover wherein I have Erred: And in the firſt Place, ſubmit the whole to your Correction; and Diſpoſal, as you think fit: Wiſhing, that both you and my ſelf, may ſo perſevere in our mutual Endeavours to do well, that in all our Greetings and Partings, we may (without Tranſgreſſing our Lord's Rule) bid each other Heartily</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105289:3"/>
            <head>ANIMADVERSIONS UPON <hi>Mijn Heer Fagels Letter,</hi> CONCERNING OUR PENAL LAWS AND TESTS.</head>
            <p>I Have at the Inſtance of my worthy Friend for the Truth's ſake, ſet ſome Hours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſeriouſly to Conſider the ſubſtance of the Letter Written by <hi>Mijn Heer Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> to Mr. <hi>James Stuart,</hi> concerning our Penal Laws for Religious Matters and Teſts: And taking this Honourable Penſioner to be an Authentick Teſtimony, of their Highneſſes of <hi>Orange</hi> Declared Opinion, <hi>THAT NO CHRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT TO BE PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TED FOR HIS CONSCIENCE, OR TO BE ILL <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SED, BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE HE DIFFERS FROM THE P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLICK AND ESTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STABLISHED RELIGION;</hi> I cannot but acknowledge a great Satisfaction of Mind, to ſee ſuch a concurrent Evidence born by their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to their Royal Father's Gracious Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in a Point, which next to the Bleſſed Goſpel of Our LORD, I take to be of the higheſt Concern to the Peace of Mankind; as tending to Introduce and Eſtabliſh Concord and Amicable Converſations, in Families, Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhoods, Cities, Common-Wealths and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, where-ever it is Embraced and Candidly Purſued: For, although it may be ſubject to different Apprehenſions, (as all other Opinions are) in the Interpretation, Limitation, or Extent of it; yet its natural Tendency is to Abate, and (as Experience of its Uſefulneſs does increaſe its Eſteem) to Eradicate that Antichriſtian and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane Temper of Mind, which under a pretence of Zeal for Religion, has provoked Men to be at Variance, Implacable and Unmerciful one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another; and inſtead thereof, to inſtil ſuch Chriſtian-like Diſpoſitions, as will encline to a Peaceable Behaviour, ſuch as is becoming thoſe, who have the Name of Chriſt (who is the <hi>Prince of Peace</hi>) called upon them.</p>
            <p>This Fundamental Maxim of their Highneſſes, (though it be venerable for its Antiquity, as well
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105289:4"/>as its Intrinſick Vertue; for its as old as Chriſtianity it ſelf) has not (as our Sences Teſtify) for a long time been Practiſed, or admitted amongſt us, as a Plea, to prevent the Perſecution or ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſage of ſuch Chriſtians, as differ from the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Eſtabliſhed Religion; and in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, is but newly upon its Reviving: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it highly concerns all, who need or expect the Benefit of it, to take care, that they themſelves be not Inſtrumental to ſtifle it in its New-Birth; for it requires a gentle and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent handling, and cannot be Introduced (as it has been thruſt out) by Force or violent Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; but muſt be meekly dropp'd and inſtill'd, by ſuch Methods, and ſuitable Demeanours, as may Commend it to, and Rivet it in the Minds and Underſtandings of thoſe, that have but lately Embraced it.</p>
            <p>You ſee by the Sequel of this Lord's Letter, That neither their Highneſſes, nor this Noble Perſon (although Grounded and Principled in this peaceable Opinion) do conceive it any ill Uſage, for Diſſenters from the publick Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Religion, to be kept out of Government, and all publick Employment and Truſt: And therefore, if ſuch, who in all other Reſpects, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Benefit thereof, are denied that ſhare of Power, Truſt or Profit in publick Stations, which they think they ought alſo to enjoy in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with others; (as any of them are qualified for it upon a civil Account, without any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Teſt impoſed) yet Chriſtian Prudence will teach him that values Liberty of Conſcience, and the free, and peaceable Exerciſe of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by that Eſteem he ought to have of it, not to hazzard the loſs of it again, by an Over-valuation of any Worldly Honour, Power or Profit, but to bear with Contentation of Mind and manifeſt Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, A Character (if impoſed by the Civil Government) of a Perſon not Capacitated for publick Employment, becauſe of his Opinion in Religion, different from the Forms of Worſhip Eſtabliſh'd in the Nation.</p>
            <p>It is a high Favour and Obligation to Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <hi>That on the Diſſenters behalf,</hi> their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes Declare, <hi>They do not only conſent, as for the Papiſts in His Majeſty's Dominions, having as much Liberty as is allowed them by the States in their Provinces;</hi> (ſcilicet, <hi>a full Liberty of Conſcience) but heartily approve of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texs having an entire Liberty, for the full Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion, without any Trouble or Hinderance; ſo that none may be able to give them tho loaſt Diſturbance on that Account.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Grace ſtrictly binds the Diſſenters to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their real Thankfulneſs to their Highneſſes, by a ſuitable Deportment, <hi>SO FAR AS IS CONSISTENT WITH THEIR D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TY TO GOD AND THEIR KING;</hi> and with ſo much the greater Circumſpection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Highneſſes (<hi>Page</hi> 21.) do alſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <hi>They cannot agree to the Repeal of the Teſts, or any of thoſe Penal Laws, by which the</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>are ſhut out of both Houſes of Parliament, and out of all publick Employments, Eccleſiaſtical, Civil and Military.</hi> And this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon afterwards, adds his own Opinion to the ſame Purpoſe: (<hi>Page</hi> 3.) And yet <hi>HE E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VER WAS, AND STILL IS, VERY M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH AGAINST ALL THOSE WHO WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE ANY CHRISTIAN, BECA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE HE DIFFERS FROM THE P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLICK AND ESTABLISHED RELIGION; AND HOPES BY THE GRACE OF GOD, TO CONTIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E STILL IN THE SAME MIND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And asks, <hi>Who would go about to perſwade him, or any Man elſe, to endeavour to move their Highneſſes, whom God hath Honoured ſo far, as to make them the Protectors of His Church, ſo approve of, or to conſent to things ſo hurtful, both to the Reformed Religion, and to the Publick Safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty's Gracious Declaration for <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience,</hi> and thoſe Paſſages foregoing, with others of the like Nature in His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Letter, being compared and duly weighed, will plainly Demonſtrate where the ſtreſs lies in Reference to Diſſenters; and how greatly it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them, that this Matter be clearly Stated, to the Satisfaction both of His Majeſty and their Highneſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THE KING OF HIS PRINCELY CARE AND AFFECTION <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTO ALL HIS LO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BJECTS, THAT THEY MAY LIVE AT EASE AND Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IET; AND FOR THE ENCREASE OF TRADE AND ENCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAGEMENT OF STRANGERS, THO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHT FIT BY VERT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E OF HIS ROYAL PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROGATIVE, TO ISS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E FORTH HIS DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CLARATION OF IND<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LGENCE; MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KING NO DO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BT OF THE CONC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENCE OF HIS TWO HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SES OF PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT, WHEN HE SHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LD THINK IT CONVENIENT FOR THEM TO MEET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Indulgence conſiſts of two principal Parts, The one Relating to Eccleſiaſtical Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105289:4"/>and the Exerciſe of Religion in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whatſoever: And the other, to Civil and Military Employments.</p>
            <p>In the former Caſe, His Majeſty having firſt Declared, That He would Protect and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all His Subjects of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the free Exerciſe of their Religion, as by Law Eſtabliſhed; (as ſhall be herein, after in the Words of His Royal Declaration, expreſs'd) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards declares His Royal Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That from henceforth, the Execution of all, and all manner of Penal Laws in</hi> MATTERS ECCLESIASTICAL, <hi>for not coming to Church, or not Receiving the Sacrament, or for any other Nonconformity to the Religion Eſtabliſhed, or for or by Reaſon of the Exerciſe of Religion in any manner whatſoever, be immediately Suſpended: And the further Execution of the ſaid</hi> Penal Laws, <hi>And every of them, is thereby Suſpended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the latter Caſe. <hi>Foraſmuch as he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to have the Benefit of the Service of all His Loving Subjects, which by the Law of Nature, is inſeparably Annexed to, and inherent in His Royal Perſon: And that none of His Subjects might for the future be under any Diſcouragement or Diſability, (who are otherwiſe well inclined, and fit to ſerve His Majeſty) by Reaſon of ſome</hi> Oaths <hi>or</hi> Teſts, <hi>that have been uſually Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred on ſuch Occaſions; His Majeſty did thereby further Declare, That it was His Royal Will and Pleaſure, That the Oaths, commonly called</hi> the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance: <hi>And alſo, the ſeveral</hi> Teſts <hi>and</hi> Declarations <hi>mentioned in the</hi> Acts of Parliament, <hi>made in the</hi> 25th <hi>and</hi> 30th <hi>Years of the Reign of His late Royal Brother King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second, ſhould not at any Time thereafter, be Required to be Taken, Declared, or Subſcrired by any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, who was, or ſhould be employed in any Office or place of Truſt, either Civil or Military, under His Majeſty, or in His Government.</hi> And further, <hi>That it was His Pleaſure and Intention, from Time to Time, thereafter to grant His Royal Diſpenſations under His great Seal, to all His Loving Subjects, ſo to be employed, who ſhould not take the ſaid</hi> Oaths, <hi>or Subſcribe or Declare the ſaid</hi> Teſts <hi>or</hi> Declarations, <hi>in the above-mentioned</hi> Acts. <hi>and every of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Lord <hi>Fagel</hi> tells us, That <hi>their Highneſſes of</hi> Orange, <hi>if His Majesty ſhall think fit further to deſire their Concurrence in the Repealing the</hi> Penal Laws, <hi>they are ready to give it; Provided always, that thoſe Laws remain ſtill in their full Vigour, by which the</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>are ſhut out of both Houſes of</hi> Parliament, <hi>and all Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employments, as has been before-mentioned. But to the Repeal of thoſe</hi> Teſts, <hi>and thoſe other</hi> Penal Laws <hi>laſt mentioned, that tend to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Proteſtant Religion, for the Reaſons expreſt in the Letter, they cannot agree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the Diſſenters upon their firſt ſenſible Experience of that great and unexpected change of their Condition, effected by His Majeſty's Gracious Declaration of Indulgence, Enlarged from Impriſonment during Life, without Conformity; diſcharged from Fines and Forfeitures, which they cou'd never have ſatisfied: At Liberty, not only to follow and attend upon their private Callings, but to Exerciſe their Religion according to their Conſciences, without any Reſtraint or Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, <hi>(ſo as they took ſpecial Care, that nothing was Preach'd or Taught amongſt them, which might any Ways tend to Alienate the Hearts of His Majeſty's Subjects from Him or His Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and that their Meetings and Aſſemblies, were Peaceably, Openly, and Publickly Held, and all Perſons freely admitted to them;)</hi> Reckoned themſelves obliged in Duty to God in the firſt place, for His Merciful Providence; To the King in the next place, for His Gracious Pardon and Indulgence, to pay their Humble and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledgments: And this they did in their Publick Aſſemblies, and alſo in their Solemn Addreſſes to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Soon after, under an Umbrage of Kindneſs in a Printed Letter, (Entituled, <hi>A Letter to a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter</hi>) they were rebuked as guilty of Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Thankfulneſs, and Pre-cautioned of the Hazzards to which they Expoſed themſelves, by taking Liberty to Aſſemble publickly (the only Condition upon which they were permitted to Aſſemble at all) before it was Granted, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliament: But (this Rebuke and Pre-caution, notwithſtanding) the Generality of Diſſenters and many others in Conjunction with them, purſued the ſame Method in Addreſſing to the King; and many of them, therein aſſuring His Majeſty of their beſt Endeavours, for Chooſing ſuch Members for the next Parliament, as would conſent, that the Indulgence granted by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Gracious Declaration, ſhould be Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a <hi>Statute-Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Diſſenters had not made theſe Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, or ſhould not purſue what they have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105289:5"/>promiſed, His Majeſty would have juſt Cauſe to be highly offended; But becauſe they have been driven to this Neceſſity by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and thoſe in her Communion, by whom they have been always branded with the Marks of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, as if they were Univerſally Seditious, Riotous, Rebellious; and all this, becauſe ſome of them Regularly, others of them Irregularly, in Conjunction with many more than themſelves of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſtrove to Defend and Vindicate their own and others Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, as Subjects &amp; Chriſtians, of which the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in Oppoſition to theſe Diſſenters, and the reſt of their own Communion, would make a Surrender, and (as the Author of the <hi>Letter to a Diſſenter</hi> terms it) <hi>a Sacrifice to their Revenge.</hi> If the Diſſenters had no other Plea, but this inevitable Neceſſity to which they were Reduced, that they muſt ſtarve at preſent, to avoid a Forfeiture of their Subſiſtance in the next Generation. It is to be hoped, that what they have done, and promiſed to do in their Addreſſes to His Majeſty, being duly weighed by my Lord <hi>Fagel,</hi> will be ſo Repreſented, as that it may not be any Offence to their Highneſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> though in ſuch things as relate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to them all, they may all agree; yet in other things, they diſſent one from another, as much as from thoſe who are no Diſſenters, ſo called in Reference to the Eſtabliſh'd Religion; and in that Coercion of Conſcience, Subjection to Fines, Impriſonments, and Univerſal Ruine, to which, by <hi>Statute-Laws</hi> as they now ſtand, they were all Expoſed. They are equally concerned in an Orderly, and ſuch a Way as is attainable with His Majeſty's Approbation and Royal Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to endeavour, that all thoſe Laws may be either Totally, or in part Repealed; and the reſt ſo Explained, as that none of them may be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the Severity of them for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>But although the Preſſures under which the Diſſenters were laid; are a ſufficient neceſſious Excuſe, for what they have done, and further ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged themſelves to do, in their Humble &amp; Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Addreſſes to the King: Yet for His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips more entire Satisfaction that their Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities have not driven them to do any more, than what is agreeable with their Principles, in Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Civil Government; and ſuch Laws as are requiſite for its Support, Dignity and Safety, ſo far as I am capable of underſtanding their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for ſo doing, by a general Converſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt moſt ſorts of them, for many Years paſt: I am deſirous they ſhould be Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated for a general Satisfaction; and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and eſpecially, that his Lordſhip may know them, if he will vouchſafe to read my Sentiments therein, who am an old Diſſenter from the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, Service, and Statute Law, Worſhip and ſome Canons; but no Adverſary to the Doctrines in general, or Conſtitution of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Lordſhip is pleaſed to ſay, <hi>(Page</hi> 4.) That <hi>it is certain, that there is no</hi> Kingdom, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, Conſtituted Body, <hi>or</hi> Aſſembly <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, in which there are not Laws made for the Safety thereof; and that Provide againſt all Attempts whatſoever, that diſturb their Peace, and that preſcribe the Conditions and Qualities that they judge neceſſary for all that ſhall bear Employments in that Kingdom, State, or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration: And no man can pretend, that there is any Injury done him, that he is not admitted to Employments, when he doth not ſatisfie the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Qualities Required.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And afterwards, (<hi>page</hi> 7.) <hi>Our Laws are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, Excluding</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>by Name, from all ſhare in the Government, and from all Employments, either of the Policy or Juſtice of our Countrey: It is true, I do not know of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Law that ſhuts them out of Military Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments; That had indeed been hard, ſince in the firſt Formation of our State, they joined with us in defending our Publick Liberty, and did us Eminent Service during the Wars, therefore they were not ſhut out from theſe Military Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for the publick Safety was no ways endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered by this; both, becauſe their Numbers that ſerved in our Troops were not great, and becauſe the</hi> States <hi>could eaſily prevent any Inconvenience that might ariſe out of that, which could not have been done ſo eaſily, if the</hi> Roman Catholicks <hi>had been admitted to a ſhare in the Government, and in the Policy and Juſtice of our State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, <hi>(page</hi> 8.) <hi>Since the matter that is now in Hand, Relates not to the making of New Laws, but to the Total Repealing of thoſe already made both by King and Parliament: Their Highneſſes do not ſee how it can be expected of them, that they ſhould Conſent to ſuch a Repeal, to which they have ſo juſt an Averſion; as being a thing, that is contrary to the Laws and Cuſtoms of all</hi> Chriſtian States, <hi>whether.</hi> Proteſtants <hi>or</hi> Papiſts, <hi>who receive none to a ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or publick Employments, but thoſe who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105289:5"/>Profeſs the Publick and Eſtabliſh'd Religion, and take Care to ſecure it againſt all Attempts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</hi> And a little before, <hi>Their Highneſſes are Convinced in their Conſciences, that both the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, and the Safety of the Nation, would be Expoſed to moſt certain Dangers, if either the</hi> Teſts, <hi>or thoſe other</hi> Penal Laws, <hi>of which I have made frequent mention, ſhould be Repeal'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſeveral of theſe things, it is my intent, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to offer my Diſſent: But I deſire to do it with all Deference to his Lordſhip, and humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Judgment and Determination of my Superiours, on whoſe Shoulders the weight of Government, whether Legiſlative, or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, lies; and in whoſe Hands reſpectively, are both the Right and Power of Diſpoſing all pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employments.</p>
            <p>Civil Government, is Ordained of God for the good of Mankind; Dominion is founded in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo of Conſequence, is Subjection to Superiours. The Diſſenters, who acknowledge the Scriptures to be the Word of God Revealed from Heaven, and to contain, the ſtanding gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rules of Faith, Worſhip and Converſation, are therein taught, and readily admit, that every Soul ought to be ſubject to the Higher Powers and to every Ordinance of Humane Creation; not only for Wrath, but for Conſcience ſake, and the Lord's ſake.</p>
            <p>Every Independent Government, being Supream over its own Subjects, is veſted with a Power to make and Execute ſuch Laws, as are neceſſary, proper, and adequate, for its own Support and Safety; and may juſtly require, not only a Subjective, Paſſive, but an Active Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be given by each particular Subject, in all Lawful Things, as he is thereto Capacitated, and by Authority Commanded.</p>
            <p>No matter or thing whatſoever, openly Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacted, is Exempted from the Cognizance or Judgment of ſuch, as are ſupream Governours, within their Reſpective Dominions: And it is certain, as my Lord <hi>Fagel</hi> ſays, <hi>There is no ſort of Government, in which there are not Laws made for the Safety thereof, and that Provide againſt all Attempts that diſturb their Peace;</hi> And <hi>(de Facto)</hi> Preſcribe Conditions and Qualities as they judge neceſſary for all that ſhall be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein.</p>
            <p>But that all Conditions and Qualities are alike, neceſſary, equal and juſt, or ſuch as naturally tend to the Peace and Safety of the Government; and that no man can pretend, that there is any Injury done him, that he is not admitted to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employments, when he doth not ſatisfie the Conditions and Qualities required: Theſe things fall under farther Conſideration.</p>
            <p>If his Lordſhip had not declared the ſpecial Reaſons, why their Highneſſes, and himſelf can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent to a Repeal of the Teſts, and ſome Penal Laws; or not mentioned the Laws of his own Country, nor declared, that the matter now in Hand, relates not to the making of New Laws, but to the total Repealing of thoſe already made, both by King and Parliament. There had been no Occaſion given for ſuch Remarks, as I ſhall now make upon theſe Branches of His Letter;</p>
            <p>His Loadſhip very well knows, that as Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are divers in their Forms and Conſtitutions, one from another, ſo alſo are their Laws and Cuſtoms.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stuart</hi>'s Miſtake, gave Occaſion to his Lordſhip to inform him aright, concerning the Laws of his Countrey; and if his Lordſhip be miſtaken, concerning the Laws and Conſtitutions of Our Kingdom, there is the like Occaſion for a Right Information therein to be given to his Lordſhip, and all others who concern themſelves therein: And as he ſubjoyns the Reaſons, why the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi>'s are not ſhut out of Military Employments, but are Excluded by Name from all ſhare in the Government, and from all Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, either of the Policy or Juſtice of their Country; ſo I may humbly offer to His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips further Conſideration, ſuch Reaſons as I think to be cogent, why no <hi>Diſſenter, Roman Catholick,</hi> nor <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> if Commanded and Authorized by the King, and in all other Reſpects (not touching his Religion) duly qualified accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Law, to Execute any Employment, Civil or Military, ſhould be Excluded from thence, purely, becauſe his Religion or manner of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is different from that, which by <hi>Statute-Law</hi> is Eſtabliſh'd to be the publick Worſhip of the Nation.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but that forementioned Maxim which tends to, and is neceſſary for the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of publick Peace and equal Juſtice, and which is before declared to be the Opinion of their Highneſſes, is built upon the ſame Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which his Lordſhip declares to be the ground, why he is very much againſt all thoſe who would (<hi>Page</hi> 3.) Perſecute any Chriſtian, becauſe he differs from the Publick Eſtabliſh'd Religion. Scil. <hi>Becauſe that Light, with which Religion Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminates Our Minds, is purely an Effect of God's Mercy to us, and inclines to Pity, and Pray for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105289:6"/>thoſe who Err, That God would bring them into the Way of Truth, and to uſe all Gentle and Friendly Methods, for Reducing them to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And his Lordſhip may very well ſay, <hi>That He could never Comprehend,</hi> (for I think, it is not to be Comprehended by any man) <hi>how any that Profeſs themſelves Chriſtians, and that may En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their Religion freely and without any Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, can judge it lawful for them to go about to diſturb the Quiet of any Kingdom or State; or to Overturn Conſtitutions, that ſo they themſelves may be Admitted into Employments.</hi> And let me add to this; from the like Reaſons of State and Obligation of Religion, I can as little appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, how any that are of the National Religion, and may enjoy both that, and all the publick Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of it freely, and without any Diſturbance, can go about to diſturb the Quiet of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and to make, not only Religious, but our Civil Conſtitutions ſo to jarr, and juſtle one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, as to threaten the over turning of the whole; That ſo under the Umbrage of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws (in ſome Reſpects incoherent, if not with the Fundamental Law, yet with the preſent State and Management of Publick Affairs,) they themſelves may be the only Perſons capable of Employments, Excluſive of thoſe many Myriads in the Nation, who upon a Civil Account may juſtly deſire, that ſuch Statute Laws may in an orderly Method, be either in part, or in whole Repealed, or ſo Limited or Explained, as that they may not for the future, be any more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of His Majeſty's Subjects, entangled in, or ſubjected to a loſs of their Civil Rights, for a good Conſcience towards God, or Obedience to the Commands of their King, in ſuch things as are in their own Nature, not only lawful, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be done.</p>
            <p>It may be his Lordſhip has not taken ſuch ſtrict notice of the Nature of the Government, Conſtitutions and different Qualities of the Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective kinds of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> as he has done of thoſe of his own Countrey; all which are neceſſary to be known, and well pondred before any Solid Judgment can be made in Reſpect of ſuch Proceedings, as have been and are like to be amongſt us, in the diſpoſal and calling of Perſons to Offices, Places of Truſt, and Publick Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip is pleaſed frequently in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to put a great Emphaſis upon ſuch Laws as he would not have Repealed, in that they are made both by King and Parliament; whereas, ſetting aſide the ſubject matter, there is nothing more in this, then what is requiſite to every Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that paſſes into a Law; ſome of which have never been obſerved at all, but openly broken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day; and no man ever Proſecuted for the breach of it: Others Prohibiting ſome ſorts of Trades and Merchandizes, which have been E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded, Neglected, or Counived at, or Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed withal, upon divers Occaſions not needful to be mentioned: Nothing is more frequent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, then to have Statute Laws made in one Parliament, to be Repealed in part, or in whole, by the next Succeeding, and ſometimes in the ſame Parliament, if of any Long Continuance, But on the other hand the Sages of our Law, have in their Law Books delivered certain Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Maxims, from which we can never recede; as that, If a Statute Law ſhould be made contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Common Right, and the General Law of Nature, Reaſon or Scripture; ſuch a Law would be void of it ſelf: And when Actions have been grounded upon a particular Statute, which in the ordinary conſtruction of words, did ſeem to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench upon any Fundamental Maxims: Our Judges have given another Interpretation of ſuch Statutes, then the words in common conſtruction would bear, rather then give Judgment in any ſpecial caſe againſt ſuch General and Fundamental Maxims.</p>
            <p>The King's Prerogative, is part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of <hi>England,</hi> and as this is expreſly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ſeveral Statutes; ſo it hath been frequently Interpreted by the Sages of our Law, to extend to the Diſpenſing with Suſpending or Pardoning of any Penalty incurred by a Statute-Law, whereby no Subject can derive a particular damage to himſelf; and wherein the Kings Power is not expreſly limited; And where the nature of the Offence is ſuch as may be diſpenſed with the King is not confined to Number, Place, or Time, for That the Law leaves indefinitely to His Pleaſure, that the Remedy may be proportionable to the Occaſion: And tho every Penal Statute is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in ſome ſenſe <hi>Pro Bono Publico;</hi> yet it may not be <hi>Pro Bono Singulorum Populi.</hi> And in ſuch caſes, the Offence is underſtood to be only to the King's damage in His Publick Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Supream Governour; and therefore wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none but Himſelf, His Prerogative may be Exerciſed as oft and as largly as he is Gratiouſly Pleaſed it ſhall be in Acts of Mercy, Kindneſs, and Goodneſs to any of His Subjects who are Obnoxious to Penalties by breach of Penal Laws, ſo as no other of His Subjects be injur'd thereby in their particular Rights: And in many caſes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105289:6"/>with a <hi>Non-obſtante</hi> in His Grant, to a <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obſtante</hi> in an Act of Parliament therein Recited.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip is pleaſed to ſay, That it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Laws and Cuſtoms of all Chriſtian States, whether Proteſtants or Papiſts, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieve none to a ſhare in the Government, or to Publick Employments, but thoſe who profeſs the Publick and Eſtabliſhed Religion, and that take care to ſecure it againſt all Attempts whatſoever; But this muſt be taken with an Exception, as to Military Employments in his Lordſhips Country, as he has expreſt it; and alſo with an Exception as to our Kingdom, which as Sr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Coke</hi> Chief Juſtice has well Obſerv'd, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, not only by the Seas, but by its own Laws from all the reſt of the World; for that they have no dependance upon any Forreign Law whatſoever, no not upon the Civil Law; but are in ſuch a manner Appropriated to it ſelf, as that no forreign Precedents are to be objected againſt it; And with this ſpecial Exception in the very Act of Parliament, for the taking the Parliamentary-Teſt in Relation to the the King's Majeſty that now is, being then Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and Heir Preſumptive to the Crown, which in Right of Succeſſion to His Royal Brother, He now Enjoys, there is a Proviſo made in theſe words, <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded always, that nothing in this Act contained, ſhall extend to His Royal Highneſs the Duke of York. (Provided)</hi> had been ſufficient, and I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume <hi>(always)</hi> will be conſtrued only as Redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant. But as there is no expreſs Saving, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any expreſs limitation of the King's Prerogative in that Act.</p>
            <p>I alſo conceive, That His Lordſhips Aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought to be taken with an Explanation, or far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Exception of ſuch Governments as by their Laws and Conſtitutions admit of the Publick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of both Religions, Roman Catholick and Reformed; and alſo of all ſuch Imperial Dyets in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> as are Conſtituted of of Princes and Palatinates, as well of one as of the other Religion. And tho I have no other Exceptions to add in matter of Fact, as it is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to Chriſtian States, yet among ſuch as are of the Reformed Religion, who acknowledge the Authority and Verity of the Holy Scripture. It may be alledged that <hi>Ab Origine,</hi> it was no General Rule, Law, or Reaſon of State, in Relation to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government, That all who were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Publick Employment, ſhould be of one and the ſame Religion; I omit to inſtance thoſe mean Examples which may be given from thence to the Contrary: I ſhall mention only that of the Babylonian and Perſian Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> gave directions to the Maſter of his Eunuchs, to bring the Choiceſt of the <hi>Iſralites</hi> for Wiſdom and Knowledge, to ſtand in the Kings Pallace; <hi>Daniel</hi> and his Brethren were brought, and ſtood before the King (tho they neither were of, nor would take any care to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Kings Religion, or the Publick Worſhip of the Countrey.) And theſe and others of their Nation were promoted by him: And the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Perſian Monarchs in Places of Truſt and Publick Employments, and obtained great Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in relation to their own Religion, Nation, Countrey, and Principal City.</p>
            <p>But it is to be obſerved, That tho, Liberty-of-Conſcience, was rarely Interdicted by any of the Great Monarchs before, or till the Age after our Saviours manifeſtation in the Fleſh; (ſo that to diſſent from any Eſtabliſhed Religion was no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to a Secular Employment) yet an Antichriſtian Spirit ever and anon diſcovered it ſelf in ſuch as had a form of Godlineſs, in their Diſturbing and Oppoſing the true Servants of God, in the Peaceable Enjoyment of their Civil and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Liberties, upon the account of their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from ſuch Forms of Worſhip as by Cuſtom or Tradition were commonly uſed. Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to the Revealed Will of God, has often been maligned, whereof we have alſo divers inſtances in Scripture, one I ſhall mention, becauſe (tho it be a digreſſion.) it ſeems apt to our preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> were (as by a ſtated Maxime) eſteemed unalterable; <hi>Cyrus</hi> their King, as alſo his Succeſſors, having experience of the Wiſdom and Fidelity of ſome of the Jews in their Captivity, not only placed them in Publick Employments, but granted them as a ſpecial Favour, the Rebuilding of their City, and the Temple of God, and Reſtitution of His Worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> according to the Divine Law.</p>
            <p>The Kings great Officers, and the Nations inhabiting in the Countries Adjacent (tho they pretended to ſeek and do Sacrifice to the ſame God yet) being Adverſaries to the Jews Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and Reformation of Divine Worſhip, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained countermands to this Perſian Kings decree, and even in the Reign of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> hired Councellors to fruſtrate the Jews purpoſes, and by Royal Orders, obtained contrary to the firſt Decree, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Progreſs, &amp; full Accompliſhment, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for many years after. And tho theſe King; had Experience of the Fidelity of the Perſons to whom
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105289:7"/>theſe Favours were granted, yet on Pretenſions that the Grants would be to the Kings damage, and that the Jews in general were (as ſome of them at certain ſeaſons had ſhew'd themſelves to be) a Seditious People: They were prevented for a long time of the full Enjoyment of the Priviledges Granted.</p>
            <p>In like manner, (ſo far as the parallel in a due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction will bear) If the States of the United Netherlands had made ſuch a Judgment Univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all that were of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> That they were and would be perſidious to their Civil Governours of another Religion; And had for that Reaſon in the firſt formation of their State, rejected thoſe <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> who joyned with them in defending their Publick Liberty; They never could have had that Experience of their Fidelity and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Service for which his Lordſhip now applauds them.</p>
            <p>It is not my part to ſpeak any thing more concerning the Engliſh Roman Catholicks upon this ccaſion, then only to refer to ſuch of our Laws, as in Ages paſt were made by them to Vindicate and Guard the Kings Prerogative, and the Rights of his Subjects, againſt the Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Clergy of that Communion: But I conceive his Lordſhip (by obſerving the different conduct of thoſe of the Reformed Religion, where they have the Government toward the Roman Catholicks, from what the Roman Catholicks is where they have the Power, and reckon themſelves ſafe towards thoſe of the Reformed Religion) hath admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred a fair occaſion to His Majeſties Subjects of that Communion, to maniſeſt how far it conſiſts with their Religion and Reſolution, (whether admitted into, or debarr'd from places of Truſt and Publick Employments) indiſpenſably to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in their Obdience to the Soveraign Majeſty of this Kingdom, and Amicable and Peaceable Behaviour towards all their fellow Subjects of the Reformed Religion. And whether they will contribute their aſſiſtance in their reſpective Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, for eſtabliſhing and preſerving <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> on ſuch a Foundation as may ſecure all ſorts of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> now, and herereafter from all Penalties and Coercion: For if by any ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration it ſhould appear we have <hi>Engliſh Roman Catholickt,</hi> like unto thoſe of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> This might perhaps make way for ſome diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to be made in future proviſions, by Law (as heretofore has been done) between ſome Roman Catholicks and others, ſo as to avoid the general condemnation of all who are of their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as other parties have been to the injury of many Thouſands) by whole ſale; and if it ſhould ever hereafter happen upon proof, That any of our Engliſh Roman Catholicks ſhould do Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Service in defence of the Public Peace and Liberty; I make no doubt but the conſequence would extend farther, with reſpect unto ſuch individual Perſons, then it did with the Papiſts in the Netherlands.</p>
            <p>For greater Fidelity to the Publick Intereſt could not be ſhewn, then to hazard their Lives, and Perſevere in their Conſtancy with the Reformed Proteſtants, in defence of their Civil Liberties, againſt Armies of their own Religion, when any Act of Treachery (as the Princes of the <hi>Philiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſaid to the King of <hi>Gath,</hi> concerning King <hi>David</hi>) might have Reconciled them to thoſe of their own Communion,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.4, 5.</note> perhaps with a ſecular Advantage to themſelves, and Hazard, if not certain Ruine of the Lives and Liberties of the Reformed Proteſtants: Certainly thoſe Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Perſons (if the Conditions of their Service were not before hand expreſly limited to a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Station) might think they were hardly uſed, to be excluded by Name for the ſake of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from all ſhare in the Government and other publick Imployments, which they had been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental with others to recover and defend.</p>
            <p>There is one paſſage more in his Lordſhip's Letter, which will lead me to what I have far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to add upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip ſays, <hi>He would gladly ſee one ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle good Reaſon, to move a Proteſtant that fears God, and that is concerned for his Religion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Repealing of thoſe Laws that have been Enacted by the Authority of the King and Parliament, which have no other Tendency, but to the Security of the Reformed Religion, and to the reſtraining of the Roman Catholicks from a capacity of overturning it: Theſe Laws inflict neither Fines nor Puniſhments, and do only Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Roman Catholicks from a ſhare in the Government; who by being in Employments must needs ſtudy to Encreaſe their Party, and to gain to it more Credit and Power, which by what we ſee every day, we muſt conclude, will be extreamly dangerous to the Reformed Religion, and muſt turn to its great Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105289:7"/>
            <p>I have before declared, I have been long reckoned among diſſenting Proteſtants, and do acknowledge it is my Duty (above all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things) to Fear GOD, and to be concerned for my Religion. But I muſt beg his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips patience and permiſſion to enquire into the true meaning of this Paſſage before I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to ſatisfy his Lordſhips deſire. (1.) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I cannot find any ſuch Law, as is effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al (our preſent State conſidered) to keep <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks</hi> and no others out of Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or that do not either directly or of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence, tend to the inflicting of Fines and Puniſhments on them, or any other Diſſenters if they reſuſe, or (without the qualifications required) accept the execution of thoſe imployments. (2.) I premiſe, there may be an Explaining, Qualiſying or Repealing any Laws in part, without a general or abſolute Repeal of the whole Law: an inſtance of this kind we have in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, in the Third year of His Reign, a Law was made for ſome perſons ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſubſcribing the Oath commonly called the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> in the form preſcribed.</p>
            <p>In the Seventh year of the ſame King, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Law was made, wherein notice is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of a juſt deſence of the ſaid Oath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt falſe and unſound Arguments, undertaken and performed by the Kings Majeſty, to the great contentment of all his loving Subjects, notwithſtanding the gain-ſaying of contentious adverſaries, and in this laſt Act it is ſaid, <hi>That the form of the Oath tends only to the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch duty, as every true and well-affected ſubject, not only by bond of Allegiance, but alſo by the command of Almighty GOD, ought to bare to his Majesty, his Heirs and Succeſſors.</hi> And Enacts. That every perſon above the age of Eighteen years, therein mentioned, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſhall Make, Take, and Receive a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Oath upon the Evangeliſts according to the <hi>Tenor and Effect</hi> of the ſaid Oath ſet forth in the firſt mentioned Statute before ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are in that Act expreſſed.</p>
            <p>In the Kings Epiſtle to all Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, Free-Princes, and States Prefixt to his Apology; his Majeſty declares, <hi>That his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in that Oath, was</hi> only <hi>to meddle with that due temporal obedience, which his Subjects owed to him, and not to intrap, nor inthrall their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences;</hi> And in Anſwer to the Popes Second Breve, <hi>That ſuch as had taken this Oath, had ſworn to no more than their Natural Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings Intent being thus declared, His Apology approved by Parliament, and the Oath Explained, ſatisfied many, ſo as to take the ſaid Oath, which otherwiſe would have ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled it.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance we have in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the Firſt year of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Reign, that Statute which preſcribes and enjoyns the taking of the Oath called the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> by all the Clergy and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Officers (whereby they obliged themſelves to aſſiſt and deſend the Queens Highneſs, her Heirs and Succeſſors in all Juriſdictions united, and annexed to the Imperial Crown of this Realm) does alſo among other things unite and annex to the Crown all Juriſdictions, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Eccleſiaſtical, which had before, or might Lawfully be exerciſed for Reformation of all manner of Errors, Hereſies and Schiſms.</p>
            <p>This Act and Oath occaſioned many ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the minds of her Majeſties Subjects; for which cauſe, ſoon after the diſſolution of this Parliament, and about four years before the Calling of the next, her Majeſty, beſides the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations which ſhe gave to particular Perſons upon ſpecial reaſons) publiſhed a Book common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the <hi>Queens Injunctions,</hi> wherein ſhe was graciouſly pleaſed, <hi>by her Power in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Affairs,</hi> to declare ſuch a conſtruction and ſenſe of the words of this Oath (expreſt in other words much different) as gave Her Subjects in general, relief therein; <hi>and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted ſuch of them, as ſhould in the ſenſe ſhe declared, take the ſaid Oath, from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Penalties</hi> (which were very great) <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch as ſhould refuſe to take the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next ſucceeding Parliament, which was held in the Fifth year of her Majeſties Reign, this Oath of Supremacy was enjoyned to be taken, not only by all ſuch perſons as were mentioned in the former Act, but alſo by every Member of the Commons Houſe of Parliament; and it was Enacted, That ſuch as ſhould enter into the Parliament Houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking the ſaid Oath, ſhould be deemed no Member thereof, and ſhould ſuffer ſuch pains and penalties, as if he had preſumed to ſit in the ſame, whithout Election, Return, or Authority.</p>
            <p>But it was alſo therein provided, <hi>That the ſaid Oath ſhould be taken and expounded in ſuch form, as was ſet forth in an Admonition annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Queens Majeſties Injunctions, publiſhed in the Firſt year of her Majeſties Reign,</hi> which was expreſt in the Act, and refer'd to the ſaid
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105289:8"/>Injunctions, by which it more plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in the Eighth year of her Majeſties Reign, in an Act then made, it is recited, <hi>That the Queens Highneſs in Her Letters Patent to any Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or others for Confirming, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting, and Conſecrating of any Perſon elected to the Office or Dignity of any Archbiſhop, or Biſhop, had not only uſed ſuch Words and Sentences, as were accuſtomed to be uſed by King</hi> Henry, <hi>and King</hi> Edward, <hi>her Majeſties Father and Brother, in their like Letters Patents, made for ſuch Cauſes, But alſo had uſed and put in her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſaid Letters Patent, divers other general VVords and Sentences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by her Highneſs, by her Supream Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Authority, had diſpenſed with all cauſes or doubts of any imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or diſability, that could, or might, in any wiſe be objected againſt the ſame.</hi> And the ſame Statute declares, That all Acts and Things done by any Perſon or Perſons, by vertue of her Majeſties Letters Patents, or Commiſſion about any Conſecration, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or Inveſting of any Perſon or Perſons, elected to the Office or Dignity of any Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop or Biſhop, within this Realm, or any other her Majeſties Dominions, ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Her Reign, ſhould be judged, and deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authority of that Parliament, at, and from every of the ſeveral times of the doing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, good and perfect to all reſpects and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; any matter or thing that could or might be objected to the contrary thereof, in any wiſe notwithſtanding; and provides, that all tenders of the Oath of Supremacy before that Seſſions, by vertue of any Act made in the firſt Seſſion of that Parliament, (which was about three years before) and all refuſals of the Oath ſo tendered by any Archbiſhop or Biſhop, ſhould be void, and of none effect, or validity in the Law; and, that no perſon or perſons, ſhould at any time afterwards be impeached or moleſted, in Body, Lands, Livings, or Goods, by occaſion or mean of any ſuch Certificate, touching or concerning the refuſal of the ſaid Oath; and in the preamble of this Act it is declared, <hi>That the State of the Clergy being one of the greateſt States of this Realm, it was thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient thereby, to touch ſuch Authorities as did allow and approve the making and conſecrating of the Archbiſhops and Biſhops to be duly and orderly done according to Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which proceedings it may appear, That the extent of the Oath of Supremacy, as it might have been taken to be by the firſt Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, was by the Queens Admonitions explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, limited and reſtrained; Any deficiences which were or might be conſtrued to be in the ſecond Act, or in ſuch words and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as were uſed by her Predeceſſors for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, Inveſting, or Conſecrating Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Biſhops, being one of the great States of this Realm, were by general words and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences in the Queens Letters Patent and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, ſupplyed. All cauſes and doubts of any imperfection or diſability, were by the Queens Highneſs, Supream Power and Authority, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the way: and all that was done purſuant thereunto, declared to be good and perfect, at, and from the time of the doing thereof.</p>
            <p>In the King's Apology before mentioned, his Majeſty reflects upon the Pope, for having in his Breve dealt both indiſcreetly with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and injuriouſly with his own Catholicks: With his Majeſty, in not refuting particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what ſpecial words he quarrell'd in that Oath; which if he had done, <hi>It might have been, that for the fatherly care the King had, not to put any of his ſubjects to a needleſs extremity, he might have been contented in ſome ſort to have reformed or interpreted thoſe words: With his own Catholicks, for either, if the King had ſo done, they had been thereby fully eaſed in that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; or at leaſt, if he would not have condeſcended to have altered any thing in the ſaid Oath, yet would thereby ſome appearance, or ſhadow of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe have been left unto them for refuſing the ſame, not as ſeeming thereby to ſwerve from their Obedience, and Allegiance unto him; but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtaid from taking the ſame upon the ſcrupulous tenderneſs of their Conſciences, in regard of thoſe particular words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein if the King does not aſſert his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to extend, to reforming the words of an Oath Eſtabliſhed by Law, for the eaſe of the Conſciences of ſome of his Subjects; yet his Majeſty plainly intimates ſome regard is to be had to thoſe, who did not ſwerve from their obedience, but were only ſtaid from taking this Oath through ſcruples of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, divers Grants were made or confirmed, and Toleration given to Strangers for exerciſe of Religion (in the Principal Cities, and Towns of <hi>England;</hi> as <hi>London, Norwich, Canterbury,</hi> and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105289:8"/>
               <hi>Southampton</hi>) in Forms different from the Act of Uniformity of worſhip, with a <hi>Non obſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te</hi> to that Act; And Charters in like manner, in the Reign of all or ſome, of the three laſt Kings, to divers of their own Subjects, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion according to their Conſciences in Forreign parts within their Majeſties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, with a diſpenſation as to Laws in force, relating to Religion, and requiring Oaths of Obedience in the form preſcribed by ſuch Laws; and though ſome of theſe Diſſenters, who obtained theſe Grants, have contrary to the common rules of Juſtice and Equity, inflicted temporal penalties upon ſuch of their brethren as have diſſented from the forms of Worſhip, eſtabliſhed by their own municipal Laws, and have therein uſurped a power over Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which they deſired, and obtained by Grant from the King, might not be exerciſed in reference to themſelves; yet thoſe Regal Grants, made to ſecure them from the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which otherwiſe they might have incurred by their Nonconformity to the General Laws in being, reſpecting Religion, Sacrament, and Oaths, (which reacht not only throughout the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> but all other their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Dominions) have been continued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, without ever being taken notice of in Parliament, as an extention of the Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative beyond the due bounds of Law.</p>
            <p>By all which inſtances it ſeems to me evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that his preſent Majeſty has not by his Gracious Declaration of Indulgence, exerciſed his Prerogative in any Caſe, or upon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Grounds, than has been done before, by his Royal Predeceſſors, reſpecting the nature of the things, but only in the degree, as it is a more general extenſive, and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Act of Grace, than any of thoſe ſpecial Grants, which have been made by his Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitors, grounded upon the moſt univerſal, and evident Maximes of Religion, and Civil Government, viz. <hi>That his Majesty may have the benefit of the ſervice of all his Loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which by the law of nature is inſeparably annext to, and inherent in his Royal Perſon,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out impoſing upon any of them ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Teſts, or Oaths, as they cannot in Conſcience to God ſubmit to.</p>
            <p>The preſent Laws, which require taking of the Sacrament, Oaths, or Teſts: in order to a reſiding in the Kings Courts, or preſence, or executing offices, and places of truſt, declare the Reaſons thereof to be in that of the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Fifth of the Late King, For prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangers, which may happen from Popiſh Recuſants, and quieting the minds of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's good Subjects. And in that of the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyeth year of his Reign. For that divers good Laws had been made for preventing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and danger of Popery in this Kingdom, had not had the deſired effects by reaſon of the free acceſs, which Popiſh Recuſants had to his Majeſty's Court; and by reaſon of the liberty, which of late ſome of the Recuſants had, and took to ſit and vote in Parliament, and for the ſafety of his Majeſty's Royal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Government.</p>
            <p>I do not remember any Law paſſed in the five years interval, between the firſt and laſt Teſt, which from the Subject matter of it, can be ſuppoſed to be influenced, much leſs carried by any Roman-Catholicks, taking a liberty to ſit and vote in Parliament; nor that any Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Catholicks were in that time, or for five years after the laſt Law, proſecuted to effect, ſo as to ſuffer the penalties incurred by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Acts. If a due obſervance and execution be the life of any Law; and if upon enquiry, it ſhould be found, that this was wanting; it may thence be infer'd (if any Roman-Catholicks did within this time reſide in this Majeſty's Court) that a Law of this nature, where the King will not incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and much more, where he will ſtay the proſecution, is but as a dead letter, and never like to attain its end in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>And when all is done that can reaſonably be thought of in this kind, it ſtill remains to be farther conſidered; whether the King in being, be not the ſole and proper judge of his own ſafety; and which of his Subjects ſhall have liberty to reſide in his Courts, and come and abide in his Royal preſence. And if after the paſſing theſe Acts, the Late King had, as his preſent Majeſty has required many of his diſſenting Subjects, Roman-Catholicks or Proteſtants (who could not in conſcience take the Sacrament, Oaths, and Teſts, in the form preſcribed) to attend his Perſon, and execute his Lawful commands with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> to theſe Poenal Laws. I ſee not how they could have been juſtified in refuſing to obey ſuch commands, nor if they therein do no more, than what they are obliged to, by their true duty, and ſervice of Allegiance; how it can conſiſt with reaſon and good conſcience, that they ſhould be proſecuted upon theſe, or any ſuch like Poenal Laws, for refuſing to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify themſelves for ſuch duty and ſervice in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105289:9"/>ſorms thereby preſcribed, which are contrary to their conſcience, when the King is pleaſed to diſſence with ſuch Laws, and is otherwiſe ſatisfied of their Fidelity.</p>
            <p>There is one thing more which the Subject matter of the Oaths and Teſts, enjoyned by theſe Laws, lead me to conſider; <hi>I</hi> take the main driſt of them, to tend to a diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion between the underſtanding and conſcience of ſome men from others, concerning the Religious Opinions, and Practice, therein to be atteſted in reference to their being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into, or excluded from the Royal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Publick Truſts and Imployments, and that the weight of theſe Laws, lies principally in ſecuring the Natural and Civil Rights of the Supream Governor and his Subjects, from being invaded by Recuſants; and though the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion might alſo be in the eye of our Legiſlators, yet the keeping out falſe Doctrines, Superſtition and Idolatry, from corrupting our Religion, was not that which was eſpecially conſidered in framing theſe Laws and Teſts.</p>
            <p>For if it ſhould be ſuppoſed, that theſe Laws (becauſe they require Teſts of a Spiritual Nature, in order to admiſſion into a Civil Imploy) are capable of any ſuch Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as may lay the weight of any Perſons being excluded from ſuch Places upon this, That they are Perſons guilty of <hi>Falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious Practices,</hi> and therefore not fit for any Truſt in the Government, becauſe the admiſſion of ſuch Perſons into thoſe Places, has a tendency to corrupt the Reformed Religion.</p>
            <p>Then it would alſo follow, That whoever is guilty of any other ſuch-like <hi>Falſe Doctrine, Idolatrous</hi> or <hi>Superstitious Practice,</hi> or of any open irreligious Crimes, rank'd with, and of as hainous a nature, and as deſtructive to all True Religion, as Theſe, are equally unfit for ſuch Places: Which Opinion, if followed, would require Teſts of another kind, beſides theſe now preſcribed.</p>
            <p>For the ſame revealed Doctrines and Rules, which inſtruct us in the Nature and Uſe of the Sacrament, and other Holy Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, do alſo inſtruct us, and give warning, That none be deceived: neither For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators, nor Adulterers, nor Effeminate, nor Abuſers of themſelves with Mankind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners (no more than <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters</hi>) ſhall inherit the Kingdom of GOD.</p>
            <p>The Spirit and Soul of the <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> which is <hi>pure and undefiled before God,</hi> conſiſts in the Exerciſe of Faith, Love, Hope, and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Graces; which do all tend to an internal Sanctity, and to a Manifeſtation of it ſelf in ſuitable acts of Piety, Charity, and Mercy: And unleſs ſuch Teſts be added, as have a tendency to diſcriminate ſuch as are Religious, from others who are openly Prophane, the teſtifying againſt one ſort of <hi>Falſe Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Idolatry</hi> only, will no more Secure our Religion againſt the growth of Irreligion or Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (which is as bad as the worſt Religious part of <hi>Popery</hi>) than if he that ſerved <hi>Malcham</hi> ſhould be excluded, when he that ſerved <hi>Belial</hi> might be admitted.</p>
            <p>But ſince this cannot be, neither is it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be, in reference to Mens enjoying their Natural and Civil Rights, it remains only to be conſidered, Why any one ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superſtition,</hi> ſhould exclude any Perſon from Publick Imployments, rather than another: And this may be (not from the nature of the Worſhip, but) from the combination of the Worſhippers againſt all others, And if this can be ſeparated, or other ſufficient Caution provided, we may be as Secure both in our Civil and Religious Liberties, when theſe Teſts are no more, as we were before they were made. And for the accompliſhment of this, nothing can have a more direct and natural tendency, than ſuch a Repeal or Qualifying of Poenal Laws and Teſts, as may ſet ſuch of the R. Catholicks as ſhall oblige themſelves to be true to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Intereſt of the Nation, upon the ſame terms of <hi>Security for enjoyment of all their Civil Rights,</hi> with the reſt of their fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, notwithſtanding their Diſſent in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>It was the great Wiſdom and Care of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, as he declares in his Apology, to diſtinguiſh ſuch of his Subjects as were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, (and the Rule will hold to every other ſort of Chriſtians) who (retaining to themſelves their religious Opinions) would acknowledge their Fidelity and Civil Obedience to their Soveraign, from ſuch others as would not ſo do: Wherein His Majeſty propoſes a due regard to be had to the Conſciences of His Subjects, in reſerence to their Religion, when they are required to acknowledge that Duty which they owe to their Civil Soveraign. And this is ſo much the rather worthy imitation, in Civil Conſtitutions, becauſe it is after the Example of God, in reference to Religious Conſtitutions;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105289:9"/>
               <hi>That no particular Perſons may be Condemned of ſuch Crimes as are charged upon the Church in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Terms, whereof they are Members, if ſo be they have kept, and can purge themſelves from the Crimes objected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This appears plainly by ſuch Tranſactions as relate to the Church, as well under the Law as in the days of the Apoſtles, when many Corrupt Doctrines and Practices were crept in amongſt them. Theſe Churches, and ſome particular Perſons in their Communion, were treated in different manner by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles: And though the Churches in general, or the Ruling part of them, have been ſeverely reprehended, and threatned to be puniſhed of God, (except they repented) for teaching or permitting ſuch Corrupt Doctrines and Practices, yet ſuch of their Communion, who kept themſelves pure, have alwaies been diſtinguiſhed from ſuch as were Corrupt. For inſtance,</p>
            <p>In the general Defection from the Purity of GOD's Worſhip, in the Reign of King <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> ſome good thing is noted to be in his Son.</p>
            <p>What greater Corruption, and Perſecution of God's Servants, than in the Reign of King <hi>Ahab?</hi> Yet even then Seven Thouſand that had not bowed their Knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> though kept ſo obſcure, as to any open Witneſs bearing to the true Worſhip of God, that the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> reckoned himſelf to be alone; and <hi>Obadiah</hi> the Governour of the King's Houſe ſignalized for his fear of GOD, and ſecretly nouriſhing great numbers of his Prophets. The Laſt of the Prophets, (as he is placed in the Scripture Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords) before the Incarnation of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the Prieſts, whoſe Lips ſhould keep Knowledge for departing out of the way, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing many to ſtumble at the Law, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the Covenant of <hi>Levi; Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for committing abominations; yet takes notice, that there were ſome who feared the Lord; and thought on His Name; for whom a Book of Remembrance was written, that there might be a future diſcerning by men, between the Righteous and the Wicked. In the daies of our Saviour upon Earth, the Doctors of the Law, <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> had made void the Commands of God by their Traditions, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying outward Coremonies under a ſhew of Sanctity, and being inwardly unclean, and full of Hypocriſie. The Queſtion is put among themſelves, Which of the Rulers or Phariſees have believed on Him? Yet upon a Scrutiny we find <hi>Joſeph</hi> an honourable Counſellor, <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> a Phariſee and Ruler, and many among the Chief Rulers, who believed on our Lord-Among the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> the Church of <hi>Thiatira</hi> is in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral commended for her Charity, Service, Faith, Patience, and Works. And the laſt to be more than the firſt; yet the Angel of that Church is reproved for ſuffering ſalſe Doctrines and Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to be taught and committed amongſt them. And ſuch as did ſo, and all that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Adultery with them, are threatned by the Lord with great Tribulations, and Death, except they repent. But the reſt of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who did not know the depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, which others Taught, had none other burthen laid on them, but that which they had to hold faſt till the Lord came. And when <hi>Myſtery Babylon the Great,</hi> the Mother of Harlots, and Abominations of the Earth, is threatned with a ſudden approaching, and utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, there is mention of a Voice from Heaven, to God's People, ſaying, <hi>Come out of her my People, that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the ſtate of the Seven Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> when theſe Epiſtles were directed to them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, be compared one with the other, great difference will appear, as to their then preſent condition, for the better or the worſe in the Accompt of God. But there is no inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of any Power given to the beſt of theſe Churches, to Unchurch the worſt, ſo long as the Lord by His long-ſuffering Diſpenſations of Providence would continue them in the ſtate of a Chriſtian Church, as to the outward form; much leſs may any private Perſon preſume by his Cenſures to Unchurch any Chriſtian Church, which was right in its firſt Conſtitution, becauſe that ſome ordinances (which ought to be kept) are therein wanting; or that many Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which ought to have been kept out) are crept in amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Nor do I eſteem it any diſadvantage to the Truth, that the ſame name which was once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly given to a Church, becauſe Right in its Conſtitution ſhould be given alſo to ſuch as continue in Succeſſion, (though they vary in many points of Doctrines) whilſt they retain the ſame Eſſential form of a Church: Nor that it includes any approbation of their Declenſion from the Truth, any more than the terming of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the <hi>Holy City,</hi> did ſo, when they had made void the Law by their Traditions: And to all their other abominations had added a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105289:10"/>with the Gentiles, to condemn and crucifie our Saviour. But on the contrary, it may be a ground for Reproof, and a means of Conviction alſo, That any Perſons ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or are ſtiled by others, to be of ſuch a Church as, according to the Scripture-Records thereof, was originally right in its Doctrine and Conſtitution, if in any thing they deviate from the Truth there once profeſt.</p>
            <p>But that which is evident to our preſent purpoſe from all theſe inſtances, is, That as on the one hand it is no excuſe before GOD, for any Perſons to follow the Doctrines, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or Examples of his Rulers in the Church, or the Church in general, when they deviate in Doctrine or Practice from the waies of God. So on the other hand no ſuch univerſal Cenſure of any Church viſible, can be juſtified, which condemns every individual Member thereof, as guilty of the Crimes objected in general againſt the Society, without leaving any room for ſuch of them as can, and are willing, to clear themſelves from the Crimes objected. And if the Crimes objected againſt the generality of ſuch as are in Communion with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Church or Sect of Chriſtians be, that they teach or receive ſuch Doctrines as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with their Fidelity and Allegiance to their Civil Soveraigns. The Queſtion to be conſidered, is, Whether it be not more Juſt and Equal, after the Example of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, to uſe ſuch methods (proper to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſeaſon as he did formerly) as may diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the Dutiful from the Diſobedient in Civil things, rather than any other methods which tend to Condemn all, without diſtinction, for the faults of many? And if ſuch a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod were introduced, and equal countenance given to all ſorts of Chriſtians, (as they may deſerve it from their Superiours) in their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Stations, leaving them to the liberty of a voluntary Choice, as to their Religion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Communion, without any coertion of Conſcience by Temporal Penalties, this would probably be the conſequence: Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they will all equally ſtrive to merit the Favour of their Soveraign, by their True Service and Duty of Natural Allegiance, or He may at leaſt the better diſcern which of them to put moſt confidence in, and towards which to uſe the greater Caution; as Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience may manifeſt, That one ſort or other of them are, by the Doctrines Taught amongſt them, rendered more or leſs obſequious to His Lawful Commands.</p>
            <p>From all theſe premiſes, although I have already in effect ſaid, That I cannot find any ſuch Law, which neither directly inflicts, nor conſequentially ſubjects any Perſons to Fines, or Puniſhments, for Conſcience ſake, which are under our preſent Circumſtances in any reſpect effectual to ſerve the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from the Attempts of Papiſts; yet it reſts, That I give his Lordſhip all the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I can, why the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> deſire a new Law may be made, that may either repeal, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe limit, or qualify the preſent Laws for Sacrament, Oaths, and Teſts, in ſuch manner, as neither themſelves, nor any others may have any juſt Cauſe to complain of any injury done to them, in their Civil Rights for their Religions ſake.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall herein offer ſuch things to be conſidered, as tend to demonſtrate that what is deſired on the Diſſenters behalf, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compatible with the true Fear of God; but that which every Proteſtant of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (who truly fears God, and admits this to be a true Doctrine, that no man may do Evil that Good may come of it) is alſo concerned as well for the ſake of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as for his Civil Intereſt to join with them in, ſo as that they may mutually agree to chuſe ſuch Members to ſerve in the next ſucceeding Parliament, as will (upon equal and juſt Terms of ſecurity to the common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Religion, and Civil Government) give their Conſents to the Repeal or Alterations and Proviſions deſired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> For that thoſe Laws which require the taking of the Sacrament-Oaths and Teſts, are rendred ineffectual, and uſeleſs for the preſent ſeaſon, and likely to continue ſo, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Generation, as to the keeping of any Diſſenter, either Papiſt or Proteſtant, out of Employments, either Civil or Military: Daily experience manifeſts this; for in every place of Dignity, Power, or Truſt, as in the <hi>KING</hi>'s Houſhold, among the Lords of the Treaſury, in the principal Courts of Juſtice, and in Military Commands, Roman Catholicks are placed. And in the greateſt Corporations, among the Aldermen, Sheriffs, and other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, both Roman Catholicks, and Proteſtant Diſſenters, by the King's Commiſſion, with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> to theſe Laws; ſo that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, by their refuſal to take the Sacrament, Oaths and Teſts, neither keep themſelves out, nor are kept out of any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105289:10"/>imployments; as my Lord <hi>Fagell</hi> ſeems to ſuppoſe, as things ſtand at preſent. And his Lordſhip is too honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Perſon,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 5, 6.</note> and too wiſe a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lititian to deſire, or think, That the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion ſhould; and will, be ſecured in the Age to come, by a multitude of Fines forfeited in the preſent Age, by ſuch perſons executing publick imployments, who are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd by a Statute-Law to be diſabled; but in fact are not, when the <hi>King</hi> by His Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, under His Great Seal, gives and grants them an Ability and Capacity, to act with a <hi>Non Obſtante</hi> to theſe Statutes; and His Pardon in like manner to every one of them; as oft as they will ask for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Second.</hi> If the Proteſtant Diſſenters that are put into publick Offices, ſhould have the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties hereafter levied upon them, they loſe but what is ſaved to them by the <hi>King</hi>'s Bounty and Clemency.</p>
            <p>For if the Poenal Laws had not been ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended by the <hi>King</hi>'s Prerogative, they would have been ruined by the Penalties and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, to which theſe Laws made them liable; and which were for a long time with ſeverity put in Execution againſt the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of them: And though ſuch of them as have read the publick Catechiſms, and Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies publiſhed by the Papiſts, if brought by proceſs of Law before any Court of Juſtice; and required to declare, Whether they did believe the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, as it is therein taught, could with a ſafe Conſcience have Anſwer'd on the Negative, yet that would not have excuſed many of them, who muſt have ſuffered the ſame Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties impoſed for not taking the Sacrament; and it might well have been reckoned highly diſingenious for ſuch as have not been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to take the Sacrament, as by Statute-Law is directed, voluntarily, and without any conſtraint, to have taken both Sacrament and Teſt, when their ſo doing, could have no other Conſtruction, but to manifeſt thereby, That they diſtruſted the KING's Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, in preſerving them from that Penalty. And in the mean while, to truſt both their Liberties and Eſtates in their publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to Worſhip, and Worſhiping againſt Statute-Laws, under no other ſhelter, but the Wing of Prerogative. But in regard the reviving the Execution of ſuch Laws will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly ruine them; whether they be in, or out of publick imployments, no man can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blame them, if in gratitude to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and for their own ſecurity for the future, they endeavour by Repeal, or ſome other Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Proviſion, to be delivered from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third.</hi> The Diſſenters have no reaſon to truſt to any Promiſes that are made under the name of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> That they ſhall have Liberty of their Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if theſe Laws be not Repeal'd: For when any Revolution ſhall happen, no man can tell upon whom to affix theſe Promiſes, any more than thoſe of the like Nature; which beſides the Royal Declaration, were generally made under the ſame name, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that which ſucceeded, <hi>viz.</hi> His Late Majeſties Peaceable Reſtauration; and even now, not long before His Preſent Majeſties gracious Declaration, a Treatiſe was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is ſtill mentioned in the Catalogue affixed to the end of ſuch Books, as ſell in great numbers; Intituled, <hi>The Vanity of all Pretenſions to a Toleration,</hi> written by no mean Perſon, or Perſons, as is evident by the Style and Method, in which it is written; ſo that if the Diſſenters do not ſay it is the Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, but feel it is the Practiſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to keep no ſuch Promiſe with Schiſmaticks. All the Anſwer I can think of, will be, Either it was not the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that made the Promiſes; or if they did, They ſee Cauſe not to perform it.</p>
            <p>And ſo, for hereafter, if Perſecution for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be revived, it was not the Church of <hi>England</hi> that repented of that Perſecution before, or as now at preſent: It was not the Church of <hi>England</hi> that perſecuted, but ſuch as the Late <hi>King</hi> made Judges and Juſtices: Therefore to avoid all future Dangers to the Diſſenters on the one hand, and all Calumny and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations under the Name of the Church of <hi>England</hi> on the other hand, ſo as to beget a right Underſtanding, and perfect Reconciling of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Proteſtant-Diſſenters: The only viſible way is to have ſuch to repreſent them in Parliament, as will join in their humble ſupplications to the <hi>King:</hi> That the National Church by Law Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, with all its Rights, may be Confirmed by a New Law (removing Temporal Penalties for the Cauſe of Religion (which have been, and will be, the occaſions of Diſcord) out of the way) on ſuch Terms as are propos'd in His Majeſties Declaration, and as may pleaſe the <hi>King</hi> in Parliament to grant it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourth.</hi> For the ſame reaſon that His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105289:11"/>would rot have ſuch Poenal Laws and Teſts repealed, as tend to ſecure the Reſormed Religion (and keep Roman Catholicks out of publick imployments, which they have not done, nor can do). It follows, where there are Laws and Teſts, which tend to keep many Perſons out of publick imployments, who are every other way qualified for it (and if they could be admitted, would by their Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, as well in their publick Stations, as by their general Converſation, not only ſecure, but greatly promote the Reformed Religion); that there ſhould be a Repeal in part, or ſuch other qualifying thoſe Laws and Teſts, as that ſuch Perſons may not for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious Non-conformity to ſuch Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Religion, as are thereby required, be excluded from publick Stations; and tho' their Highneſſes Conceſſions be very large on behalf of ſuch Perſons, yet this may extend to ſuch Laws, as his Lordſhip might not have in his Thoughts, when he writ his Letter, <hi>viz.</hi> one made in the <hi>Thirteenth,</hi> and another in the <hi>Fourteenth</hi> Year of the Reign of His Late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>King CHARLES</hi> the <hi>Second;</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> for Regnlating of Corporations, reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Civil Offices; the <hi>Second,</hi> for Uniformity of publick Prayers, Adminiſtration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and other Rites and Ceremonies, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Clergy, Maſters, and Fellows of Colleges, and School-Maſters: By one of theſe Laws great Change of Hands was made in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Imployments throughout all the Cities and Corporations in <hi>England;</hi> and by the other of them, at leaſt 1500 Miniſters were depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their Benefices; many of which, were ſam'd abroad by their Works; and at home, for their profound Learning; and exemplary Piety.</p>
            <p>And how much theſe Alterations and Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations have tended to the Security of the Reformed Religion; and left any ſort of men, out of a capacity to hurt it, ſuch as have liv'd, and been of age and ſobriety of Mind to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in what degree the Converſation of Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes have in <hi>Twenty five</hi> Years paſt, varied from what they were <hi>Twenty five</hi> Years before, are beſt able to give a true Relation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifth,</hi> Becauſe of that doleful experience which this Iſland has had, of the ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of all ſorts of Religious Laws and Teſts, with Temporal Penalties annext; By which for theſe 50 years paſt, at divers Seaſons each different party of Proteſtants al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternately as they have had power in their hands, or countenance of Authority, have impos'd upon ſuch as differ'd from them in forms of publick Worſhip, principally upon this point, to thruſt and keep each other out of places of Truſt, and publick Imployment, which has viſibly and ſenſibly done more hurt to the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than all the attempts of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries could otherwiſe have effected. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly calls upon them all to ſurceaſe from all ſuch riged courſes, which none of them can now either in Conſcience or Prudence defend, and by a joynt concurrence to endeavour a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of all ſuch occaſions of offence out of the way, that it may not be in the power of any, who wait for opportunities, under colour of Law, to ſet Proteſtants at variance amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; that they may bite, devour, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by one another; and let not any appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, that ſuch a courſe at this Seaſon will let in Papiſt amongſt them, into Civil or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary imployments, cauſe them to neglect the preſent opportunity; for ſeeing the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of theſe Religious Laws and Teſts, with temporal Penalties annext; neither does, nor can keep them out: it is certainly more ſafe (if there were no natural equity or right in the caſe, and much more ſince there is ſo) to let them in under due cautions by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Law, than to tempt them to get all the power they can into their own hands by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary means, becauſe they cannot be ſecur'd by Law in the enjoyment of Civil Priviledges, equally, and in common with others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixth,</hi> Becauſe of that neceſſity we are under, of making one more experiment, whether thoſe of the Communion of the Church of England, Proteſtant Diſſenters and Roman Catholicks, cannot live peaceably together, and maintain a good correſpondence in places of publick truſt and imployments, notwithſtanding their different Sentiments in Religion. For his Majeſty has actually min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled and placed together ſome of each ſort in many Commiſſions for publick truſts and imployments; And if it be ſo, as my Lord <hi>Fagell</hi> aſſerts, <hi>That plain Reaſon, as well as Experience, of all Ages,
<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> That Preſent, as well as the Paſt, ſhews, That it will be impoſſible for Roman Catholicks and Proteſtants, when they are mixed together in places of truſt, and publick imployments, to live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peaceably, or to maintain a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence together, they will be certainly alwaies jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous one of another; for the principles, and maximes of both Religions are ſo oppoſite to one another, that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105289:11"/>in his opinion he does not ſee how it will be in the power of any Prince, or King whatſoever, to keep down thoſe ſuſpitions and animoſities which will be apt to ariſe upon all occaſions.</hi> This certainly calls for ſuch a neceſſary and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proviſion to be made by a new Law, for prevention of ſuch Suſpition and Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as cannot be expected from our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Religious poenal Laws and Teſts. In order thereto, His Majeſty by his gracious and prudent Conduct, in the Exerciſe of His Prerogative has laid the Foundation: And that it may be perpetuated, doubts not of the concurrence of His Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, to eſtabliſh and confirm it by a Law: And herein His Majeſty propoſes a Variation from the Laws and Cuſtoms of all ſuch other States, as my Lord <hi>Fagell</hi> mentioned, who receive none into a ſhare in the Government, or to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Imployments, but thoſe who profeſs the publick and eſtabliſhed Religion. It is not material to enquire how the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all Ages has manifeſted that to be impoſſible, which no State would ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to be tryed; but it is to our purpoſe to take notice, That where any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Party of Men, have been born hard upon by the Laws and Government in their Civil Rights for their Religions ſake; their uneaſineſs therein, has inclined them to lay hold of any occaſion to free themſelves from ſuch Preſſures; and as they appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended it did ariſe from the Religious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of ſuch as oppreſt them; ſo they have fallen in, which ſuch others, as by their profeſt Religious Principles offered them eaſe; thus promoting Civil Contentions, under a ſhew of regard to Religion to the mutual Injury of each other conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Party, beyond what the matter requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or can be juſtified by any Principles, or Maxims of the Chriſtian Religion: It is therefore much more plain Reaſon, ſince we are providentially put upon this new Experiment, which we cannot avoid, that our Statute-Laws be ſo formed, as may beſt Anſwer the natural and preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Civil Government, which is neceſſary to be done, and may be done with Juſtice, Prudence and Safety, becauſe we cannot ſhape the preſent Conſtitution of our Civil Government, to the preſent form of all our Statute Laws, for to attempt the reducing of any Civil Government, or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Body in being, who have power in their hands, and a Legal Right to order things neceſſary for their Eaſe and Safety, to ſuch a ſcantling as to ſhape and ſquare their Actions by ſuch former Satute-Laws, and Methods, as agree not with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conſtitution, is altogether as irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, as to attempt the clipping and paring the Limbs of any Natural Body, to the proportion of an old-faſhioned ſtrait Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he has over-grown, rather than to ſhape him a new Garment pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to his natural Growth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventh.</hi> One grand promoter of thoſe Diſcords, which for <hi>Fifty</hi> Years paſt, have at ſeveral times happened in His Majeſties Kingdom of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> has manifeſtly been Coercion of Conſcience, incapaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating many for publick Truſts and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and inflicting of Temporal Penalties for Non-conformity to ſuch Forms of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Religious Teſts, as have been by Statute Laws and Ordinances, impoſed upon ſuch as diſſented from the National, Eſtabliſhed Worſhip; ſometimes of one ſort, other times of another, or upon all ſorts of Diſſenters together. If any Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, or Experience would teach us, we have had ſufficient of this ſort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to make us ſo wary for the future, as not to run the hazard of any extream Revolutions, but rather to imbrace the preſent Occaſion offered, for rooting out all Inclinations to Civil Diſſentions, for different Apprehenſions in the Myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Doctrines of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>For though it be granted, That Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ever was, and alwayes ought to be eſteemed the chief intereſt of every Perſon; and that a chief part of the Civil Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns and Magiſtrates Work, is to guard, defend, and provide for it, ſo as that no Perſon, who is ſober, honeſt, and juſt in his Life and Converſation; and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges the Worſhip of GOD, according to his Conſcience, and meaſure of his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſhould be ſubjected to any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Loſs or Penalties, for the ſake of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: And though it be alſo acknowledged
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105289:12"/>as a great Bleſſing to any Nation, which hath ſuch Rulers, as will countenance, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, and provide for ſuch as are godly, and able to inſtruct others, in ſuch Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, as are according to Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>Yet it is withal to be conſidered, that Natural Religion, or Chriſtian Religion, (which is ſuperadded to natural Religion that we may be thereby inſtructed in, and better qualified for the diſcharge of our duty, whether in a Publick or Private Capacity towards God and all men) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creates nor diſſolves any Title to an Earthly Poſſeſſion, nor any Natural or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Order, wherein one Perſon ſtands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to another, but leaves every man to uſe and enjoy all that properly appertains to him on a Natural or Civil Account, in that reſpective Station, either of Rule or Subjection, wherein, by the providence of God, he is born or placed, and continued in the World.</p>
            <p>No perſon is, Husband or Wife, Parent or Child, Maſter or Servant, Magiſtrate or Subject, Landlord or Tenant, in vertue of his Religion; nor can any perſon in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate capacity invent a plea under any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of conſcience to God, (be the Religion he profeſſes true or falſe) to juſtify his treſpaſſing, or breaking in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the natural or civil Rights of another, becauſe he differs from him in his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Opinions, or manner of Worſhiping God; but every ſuch ſort of pleading, would appear to the common ſenſe and reaſon of mankind, upon the firſt view, to be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion, both upon the ſoveraignty of God; and all Civil and Religious Order, and to have no other tendency, but to turn all things into conſuſion.</p>
            <p>Natural and Civil Government are of Divine Ordination; and ſo is alſo Religion; but each of theſe are diſtinct from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in their foundation, continuance, and uſe. They are both ſo ordained of God, that they may, and ought to ſubſiſt together, and both thrive beſt when they retain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves within their diſtinct Sphears and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without incroaching one upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, only with this difference, that natural and civil Government may be preſerved where all other parts of Religion, except what relates to natural and civil Order is rejected; but Chriſtian Religion cannot be preſerved in any Society or Family, where Natural and Civil Government is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed; for the preſervation of Natural and Civil Order, is of the Eſſence of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>And whatever may be pretended under colour of Religion, ſo far as it has any ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, to diſturb the Order of Nature, it is Vain and Irreligious.</p>
            <p>Both theſe being of Divine Ordination: By the former, we are obliged to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to ſuch Laws and Rules, as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and neceſſary to the Support, Safety, and Ornament of Natural and Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for without ſuch Rule and Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no Family, or Civil. Society, whether they be Religious, Irreligious, or mixt, can ſubſiſt: By the latter, That Soveraignty, which GOD has originally, and alwaies reſerved to himſelf, in, and over every Soul that is Born into the World, in reference to the acknowledgment and worſhip of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (according to the dictates of Natural Conſcience; and that meaſure of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Divine Will, which he has Revealed, and in various meaſures given to every Soul) is preſerved, and thereby Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is propagated in Individuals.</p>
            <p>Every particular Believer is a Member of that Myſtical Body whereof the Lord Chriſt is the Head, and owes an impartial Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all his Lord's Inſtitutions, reſpecting either his private Devotions or publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblings. But ſuch may be the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Man's Liſe, or ſtate of his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as that he may not have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, or good ground, to Juſtifie his join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to any Publick Aſſemblies. In this Caſe I leave it to every one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it to God, and to ſuch as may have an authority over him in the Church of GOD; it not being my purpoſe to intermeddle in theſe things, any otherwiſe than as I conceive they relate to Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>Civil Societies cannot be ſupported with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a concord and mutual aid, either in a Politick or Martial Station. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect each Perſon is accountable for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Charge, to his next Superiour in degree; and all to Him or Them in a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105289:12"/>Capacity or legal Conſtitution, who are Supream; for <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt is ſelf cannot stand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Soveraignty of GOD, in matters of Religion, over All; and the Rule and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of One, or more, over others, in things of a Natural or Civil Relation, being both of God's ordination, (though diſtinct in their reſpective Foundations) the one in Grace, the other in Nature. Yet,</p>
            <p>No Caſe can be reaſonably ſuppoſed to ſet them at any ſuch variance, one againſt the other, as that they cannot by the Rules of Juſtice be reconciled; for he that has or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them both, is the God of Order, and hath likewiſe appointed ſuitable means, that both of them may concurr with, and aſſiſt each other. Natural and Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Religion, by Countenance, Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and Protection; Religion Natural, and Civil Government by inſtruction; and ſo each of them may accompliſh their reſpective ends, for which they are ordained of GOD.</p>
            <p>And if this be granted, it will neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow, That all thoſe Diſcords which are raiſed between them, are occaſioned by ſuch humane Uſurpations upon one, or the other of them, as are not according to God's Ordination. And of ſuch Uſurpations of Natural, Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical Rulers, over the Conſciences of their reſpective In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours; and of Eccleſiaſtical Rulers over the Conſciences, and Civil Rights alſo, of their Superiours in a Civil Relation, all ſorts of men have too often, and too long felt the ſad, experience. Bleſſed of GOD may he be, who in this reſpect propoſes himſelf to be a Peace-maker, and to ſettle each Intereſt upon its proper Foundation. For Natural, Civil, and Eccleſiaſtical Rulers, by the Ordination of GOD, are not a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to any good Work, but are, and ought to be ſo, to all that is evil, elſe their power would be given them in vain.</p>
            <p>But the Exerciſe of the Power of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Civil Rulers, in reſpect to acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Civil and Moral Nature, are of one ſort, and that of Eccleſiaſticks of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And (as before) each of theſe do beſt in their diſtinct kinds, when they keep a due <hi>Decorum</hi> within their reſpective hounds.</p>
            <p>No Natural or Civil Superiour can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretend to an Authority from GOD, to keep the Chriſtian Religion out of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, City, or Kingdom; for if that were ſo, the Maſter or Ruler, who is himſelf Irreligious, Idolatrous, or Prophane, might abridge all that are of his Family, or Subjects, of the means of their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Salvation. The Parent or Maſter may, and ought to inſtruct their Children and Servants in the Knowledge, Religious Fear, and Worſhip of GOD. And if any Child or Childiſh Servant (who with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Age, and exerciſe of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and Underſtanding, is not <hi>ſui Juris</hi>) refuſe to read any Divine Author, or to learn or repeat by Memory ſuch Leſſons, or to attend upon any Religious Exerciſe, which the Father or Maſter appoints: Such refuſal requires a due Correction; for in ſuch a Child or Servant (who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands not how to diſtinguiſh between a Religious and Moral Act, nor what it is to Worſhip GOD in Spirit and in Truth) it is an Immoral Diſobedience, and Breach upon the Natural and Civil Rule of the Parent or Maſter, as much as if they had refuſed any neceſſary Labour; but when ſuch a Child or Servant arrives to ſuch an Underſtanding, as to chuſe, or refuſe any Article or Act of Religion, as it agrees with, or is againſt his Conſcience and Knowledge of the Will of GOD, and manner of his Worſhip, in ſuch a Caſe he ought not to be coerced by any Temporal or Corporal Penalties, either by Parent or Maſter, to act againſt his Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Civil Laws reſpecting ſuch actions as purely relate to the Chriſtian Religion, if they be only Declaratory of what GOD commands or forbids, in reference to His Worſhip, may be greatly Inſtrumental to promote true Piety, if no Temporal Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be annext, nor Civil Rights thereby invaded.</p>
            <p>Temporal Penalties are proper Remedies to Correct the Diſturbers of Civil Order; Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures are a like proper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to purge a Spiritual Communion from Errours and Hereſies, if no Writ, <hi>de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicato Capiendo,</hi> attend upon ſuch Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105289:13"/>
            <p>But as no Natural or Civil Rulers may compell any Perſon (who is of years of Diſcretion to judge of his own Religious Actions, and therein with Faith and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to commit his Cauſe to GOD) by Temporal Penalties, to profeſs or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any Myſterious Doctrine or Worſhip, purely relating to the Chriſtian Religion, or to be of any Spiritual Communion: So neither may any Spiritual Congregation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their Cenſures any farther, than to expell a diſorderly Perſon out of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>No man may be driven againſt his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Conſcience, to go out of his Worldly State into a Church. Nor may any man, who is expell'd out of a Church, be driven any farther than out of his Spiritual Communion, back again into his Worldly Eſtate.</p>
            <p>An Excommunicate Husband, Parent, or Maſter, does not by his Spiritual Faults for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit his Natural or Civil Rule over his Wife, Children, or Servants; though the one be retain'd in their Spiritual Communion, and the other caſt out, yet the Communicants ought to diſcharge their Natural and Civil Duties of Obedience to the Perſon Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; for no Natural or Civil Bonds are diſunited meerly by a Diſunion in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Communion.</p>
            <p>This being a matter of voluntary choice, both as to his entrance into, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in ſuch a Communion ſo long, and no longer, than he approves the Terms, and obſerves the Rules of a Spiritual Nature, which are proper and requiſite for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. The other is fixt by ſuch natural and civil Obligations, as are not ſubmitted to his Choice at any time, until the ſet-terms on which he ſtands ſo related, are by the like natural or civil diſcharges fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd or determined. And if theſe things conſiſt with Chriſtian Religion, as it reſpects Spiritual Communion, and Domeſtick Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, much more ought they to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in reſerence to Subjects Civil Relation to their Soveraign Prince: For in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſe they only reſpect the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance of a natural or civil Peace and Concord, in a Domeſtick State, for a ſeaſon. Wherein the Publick is no otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, than to correct (not ſpiritual, but) unnatural and uncivil Diſorders, if any ſuch happen. But in the general Caſe, the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of the Subject to the Civil Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his Soveraign, is of an Univerſal Influence, and perpetual Continuance in Succeſſion, whether they be, or continue to be of the ſame, or different Opinions of Religion: Whence no man in particular can diſcharge himſelf till Death puts an Iſſue to the Obligation.</p>
            <p>Every open Immoral Act, Undutiful Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of any Perſon, towards ſuch as are his Superiours in a Natural or Civil Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Injurious Dealing with his Neighbour, and whatever other Crimes are openly committed againſt the Light of Nature, and common Reaſon of Mankind, fall natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and neceſſarily under the Civil Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour's Cognizance and Juriſdiction, to be corrected with Temporal Penalties, as may be moſt conducing to the Security, Peace, and Welfare of the <hi>Civil Government,</hi> being the <hi>immediate, Concern</hi> thereof. And all ſuch things as reſpect meerly the Natural and Civil Rights of Men, are to be moderated and judged by ſuch as have the Government and Judgment of them, in right of their Natural or Civil Stations; and if wrong Judgment proceed in any particular Caſe, yet it may be ſubmitted to <hi>A Priviledge, which might be inſiſted on, may be waved.</hi> A precept obeyed, without any offence to GOD; for Religion is no otherwiſe concerned in Things of this Kind, than as it obliges to give due obedience to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and teaches to exerciſe ſelf denyal; ſo that a quiet Submiſſion, to an unequal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, may be not only without Sin; but well pleaſing to God; but in reference to Acts of Divine Worſhip, eſpecially, ſuch as relate to the Doctrine and Duties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion; they are to be performed in Faith, and according to that meaſure of Faith and Knowledge, which every Perſon, who performs any ſuch part of Worſhip, hath attained of the revealed Will of the Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble GOD, who is the Object of ſuch Faith and Worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105289:13"/>
            <p>In this reſpect the Divine Rule, which is our Guide in Religion, directs us to walk by it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.</note> according to our preſent Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, till we arrive at a further degree of Faith and Knowledge.</p>
            <p>Opinions in Religion are ſubject to vary in one and the ſame Perſon, as he by his own ſearch and inſtruction from others is convinced of any <hi>Truth</hi> which he before conceived to be an <hi>Error,</hi> or of any <hi>Error</hi> which he before embraced as a <hi>Truth:</hi> And in this reſpect no Human Law, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing a ſtated perpetual form of Religious Worſhip (which doth neither directly, nor of due conſequence relate to the Civil Rights of <hi>Soveraign</hi> or <hi>Subject,</hi> or to the general or invari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Laws of <hi>Nature</hi>) can be the adequate Rule of every Mans Faith or Religious Worſhip in a whole Nation, becauſe, tho it ſhould command what is lawful in it ſelf, yet if it be not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to be ſo in the Mind and Conſcience of him who is required to Obey, it cannot be by him performed in Faith, without which its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible therein to pleaſe God: And if any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Act, either for matter or manner, be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by a Human Law (and not forbidden by the Law of God, or common Reaſon of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, reſpecting either Divine Worſhip or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Human Policies) which is apprehended by a particular Subject to be commanded of God; if he forbear to do it, becauſe of ſuch a human Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, that can be no excuſe for him before God.</p>
            <p>And as it is with him who is to Obey, ſo is it alſo with reſpect to the Legiſlators who make thoſe Religious Laws: The Divine Laws which reſpect the eſſential parts of the Worſhip of God are in themſelves invariable, and not to be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any human Authority; but when any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who have the Soveraign Power make any Laws reſpecting Religion, its preſumed they are made according to the preſent meaſure of the Legiſlators underſtanding of the Will of God therein. And if we look back to what hath happened in this kind among our ſelves in former as well as in this laſt Age, we may find that the Mutations herein made by Statute Laws and Ordinances, has demonſtrated a change in the Minds of our Legiſlators: every ſucceeding Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation carrying in it ſelf an evidence of an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror or Defect apprehended in the former Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment.</p>
            <p>The Rules relating to Chriſtian Worſhip, which are given in the Scriptures are Conſtant and Permanent, always one and ſame, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of theſe do not only admit and approve of great variety in ſeveral matters relating to the Worſhip of God, but forbid the Rulers of the Church, or any Church in general to impoſe an Uniformity upon the individual Members of their Communion. In the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> (<hi>Re mans</hi> 14.) ſuch as were Strong might diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves doubtful or myſterious Foints in matters of Religion; but ſuch as were Weak were not to be ſummoned to, or determined by the Reſolutions of the Strong; One that was weak in Faith would eat Hearbs, and drink no Wine, another that was ſtrong believed he might eat all things and drink Wine; each of theſe are left to their Liberty, and forbid to impoſe their Latitude or Scruples one upon another; one Man eſteemed one Day above another, and regarded it to the Lord; another Man eſteemed every Day alike, and did not regard it to the Lord. And the Rule in their Caſe is plain and poſitive, every Man was to be a Rule to himſelf, to do therein or forbear as he was perſwaded in his own Mind, <hi>for whatſoever is not of Faith is Sin:</hi> They were all forbid to judge one another, and every Man herein left to give an account of himſelf to God, and not to Judge, ſet at Nought, or give an Offence to his Brother.</p>
            <p>In the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.) a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude was allowed to the reſpective Members to Preach and Pray in different Languages and Forms, ſo as they were each of them performed with the Spirit and Underſtanding, and (by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to the Unlearned) all to Edification. The Church were not to forbid any of their Members ſpeaking with Tongues, but to ſee to it that all things might be done to Edifying, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in Order.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles Advice was in ſome Caſes <hi>To ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from Marriage,</hi> but not to forbid Marrying. And his general Behaviour among and towards the <hi>Jews</hi> in obſerving ſome Rites in eſteem with them in one manner among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner quite different, becoming all things to all Men that he might gain ſome; To them that were under the Law, as being under the Law himſelf; To them that were without the Law, as being himſelf without the Law. And yet in all this variety of his Behaviour in Religious Matters, and Religious Societies, and Converſation, not without a Law to God, but under a Law to Chriſt. So that if any Church by its Cannons tye all the Members thereof under pain of Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105289:14"/>to ſuch an Unlformity in Worſhip, as tends to abridg any individual Members thereof, that Liberty which is granted by the Apoſtle in any of theſe Particulars they therein vary from the invariable Rules of our Lord; and if the Churches or Eccleſiaſtical Rulers within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves might not impoſe any ſuch terms of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion as might deſtroy this Liberty, nor bring any of their Members under any Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures or Judgments for taking a liberty to Diſſent from the reſt, in not obſerving a Day to the Lord, when others would do it, or for Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping in other Manner and Form then the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Church would do, (ſo as the Church were not thereby interrupted in their publick Worſhip) Certainly, by a Parity of Reaſon, this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> ſhould not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed by any Human Laws inflicting temporal Penalties for Non-conformity to the Days and Modes of Worſhip preſcribed by ſuch Laws, when it is evident ſuch Human Laws have been in proceſs of time, and may be again (from the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before expreſſed) ſubject to ſuch Mutations, as to inflict Penalties for doing that at one time, as if it were in its ſelf a Crime, which at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time they command, under the like Penalty, to be done, as if it were a poſitive and indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Duty; And the removing of all temporal Penalties and Incapacities from ſuch Religious Laws and Teſts ſeems to be ſo much the more reaſonable, because it has always been and is granted on all Hands, That the Natural and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Rights of a Supream Governour are neither more or leſs, whether his Conſcience or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on agree with or differ from the Religion Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Statute Laws within his Dominions, and the ſame reaſon may hold, that ſuch of his Subjects alſo, as differ from the Eſtabliſhed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, may notwithſtanding their different Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents therein, be upon an equal Foot with the reſt of their fellow Subjects, as to the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Civil Rights or Priviledges; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering that it is not eſſentially neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to, nor under the immediate care or concern of the Civil Government, that all their Subjects ſhould be compelled by any temporal Penalties or Diſabilities to be of one and the ſame Religion, and that by other Cautions a of Civil, and not of a Religious Nature, the Peace and Security of the Civil Government may be ſufficiently provided for.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The contemplation of that ſeries of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, which has of late Years been manifeſted amongſt us, adminiſters ſome ground for caution. That we do not irregularly reſiſt the effects of it, nor fret under it, ſo as to tranſgreſs the general Laws of Government, by adhering too much to the Letter of ſome Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws, which agree not very well with the preſent ſtate of it, and may admit of an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without the breach of any Divine Law, if a Liberty for every Mans exerciſe of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the Dictates of his Conſcience, (guided by common Reaſon, and the meaſure of his Underſtanding of the Will of God therein) with Security to his Natural and Civil Rights, be of more value in its ſelf, then an Uniformity in any Mode of Worſhip, which is not of choice or voluntary, but conſtrained by temporal Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; Then what the <hi>King</hi> deſires herein ought to be complyed with for its own ſake: And if too much inſiſting on an outward Form of Godlineſs, under colour of Law, or exerciſe of Power, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the prophaning of the Sacred Myſteries to ſo mean a uſe, as not only to keep, or turn Men out of civil Imployments, but to make them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the granting or denying a Licenſe to ſell <hi>Ale,</hi> &amp; ſo little regarding the Power of Godlineſs, may be a juſt cauſe from above to make us fear o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Exerciſes then we have yet felt; it is high time for us to ſeek after ſome other means to preſerve our Religion and Civil Rights, then by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Laws in Force, as have given occaſion, or have been made uſe of to countenance ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of the Sacred Myſteries; And whatever our Fears may juſtly ſuggeſt, as to future Events, it ſeems to be much more juſtifiable and prudent to ſubſcribe to, and alſo improve the preſent Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Providence, by all ſuch means as are agreeable with our preſent Duty to God and the <hi>King,</hi> and equal right-doing to all Men, and thereby to ſeek and ſecure the peaceable and fre-exerciſe and enjoyment of our Religious and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Rights in ſuch Methods as are propoſed by his <hi>Majeſty</hi> for this preſent Age (leaving the Events in Ages to come, to the iſſues of the ſame Divine Providence which has brought us to the ſtate we are now under) then by reſiſting the preſent Occurrences thereof, and contending to maintain a particular Intereſt, to the prejudice of man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who are not wrapt up therein, (under colour of ſome preſent Laws not agreeing with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of our Government) to hazard all our Settlement during this Age, upon a preſumption we may in the Generation to come obtain a better
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105289:14"/>Settlement, which preſumed better Settlement is ſo only in eſteem with relation to ſuch Intereſts as may be therein comprehended excluſive of many, and we know not, nor have any certainty how many or what Intereſts ſhall be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein, or excluded thereout. For ſuch as acknowledg the Divine Providence, in bringing about the Changes in Government which have already hapned, and are viſible amongſt us, will be ſafe and quiet (at leaſt in their Conſciences) in doing that which is indiſputably lawful in its ſelf, if not a preſent indiſpenſable Duty, and truſting to the ſame Providence, as to future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, whatever may happen. Then any can be who ſhall be Inſtrumental to hinder our preſent Settlement in oppoſing ſuch a Courſe as is lawful in its ſelf, and contending in ſuch a manner as is manifeſtly inexpedient for the preſent Seaſon, (and very diſputable at the leaſt, whether it be conſiſtent with our preſent Duty to <hi>God,</hi> and to our <hi>Soveraign</hi>) in caſe the immediate Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or future Occurrences of ſuch an oppoſition ſhould prove otherwiſe then they expect or deſire.</p>
            <p n="10">X. Another Conſideration ariſes from the termes of the laſt Teſt and tendency of the Law by which it is Eſtabliſhed. The Law is perpetual, and reaches not only to the then preſent <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen,</hi> but to their <hi>Royal Succeſſors Kings</hi> or <hi>Queens</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And if any Subject (to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity) who ſhould at any time afterwards be convict of <hi>Popiſh Recuſancy</hi> come adviſedly into, or remain in the Preſence of the <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Queens Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> or into the Court or Houſe where they or any of them Reſide, he ſhall incur and ſuffer all the Pains, Penalties, Forfeitures and Diſabilities in that Act mentioned or contained, unleſs every Perſon ſo Convict do reſpectively in the next Term after ſuch his coming or remaining take the Oaths, and make and ſubſcribe the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſcribed in his <hi>Majeſties High-Court of Chancery:</hi> And if any <hi>Peer,</hi> or Member of the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> or Member of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> ſhall preſume to do any thing contrary to that Act, he ſhall be thenceforth deemed and adjudged a <hi>Popiſh Recuſant,</hi> convict to all intents and purpoſes whatſoever, And ſhall Forfeit and Suffer as a <hi>Popiſh Recuſant</hi> convict: This laſt Clauſe is ſomewhat unuſal, for it might have ſufficed if a <hi>Proteſtant Peer</hi> or <hi>Member</hi> preſumed to do any thing contrary to that Act, that he ſhould ſuffer like Penalties as a <hi>Popiſh Recuſant,</hi> without being deemed or judged a <hi>Popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> Convict, for that lays him under many more Penalties, beſides thoſe innumerated in that Act; but that which relates to the <hi>Queens Majeſty</hi> for the time being, is more obſervable in reference to Her Servants and Attendants; for the Proviſo which was proper for the then preſent <hi>Queen,</hi> who is now the <hi>Queen Dowager,</hi> that nothing in the Act ſhould relate to any Perſon being a natural born Subject of the <hi>King of Portugal,</hi> who ſhould then or afterward be a Sworn Servant to the <hi>Queens Majeſty,</hi> not exceeding at any one time Nine in Number, is not ſo proper to Her <hi>Royal Succeſſor,</hi> Her preſent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> nor will be to any other ſucceeding <hi>Queen,</hi> if a Native of <hi>England,</hi> or of any other Kingdom except <hi>Portugal,</hi> to whom this Act equally extends, who is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by permitted to have any one Man Servant or Officer to attend Her Royal Perſon, except he be a <hi>Portuguize</hi> by Birth, without being liable for ſuch his Service, to all the Penalties of this Act, if he perform not all the Conditions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>It may be alſo obſerved, that the <hi>Teſt</hi> relates to the then preſent uſe in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Teſt</hi> being a ſolemn Atteſtation in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> of the Atteſtants Belief con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the matters to be teſtified and declared requires in the nature of it ſome what more then a general Report or Tradition, how the uſage then was in the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And it is not impoſſible to conceive that a Hundred Years hence, or at ſome Seaſon or other, within leſs then that time, the uſage in the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> may be very different from what they were then, as to the matters declared in the <hi>Teſt,</hi> to be <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous:</hi> Neither can it be ſo well comprehended as it ſhould be in a ſolemn Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of an Article of a <hi>Chriſtians Belief</hi> in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> what may be intended by the uſage in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> whether univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of every Member who is in Communion with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> (for it cannot be ſuppoſed to be ſtrictly tyed to the <hi>Church</hi> in the City of <hi>Rome</hi>) or to the generality of that Communion, wherein many Perſons may be comprehended, who will not altogether decline or ſeparate their Communion from the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> tho' they do not Believe or Practice all theſe things as they are decreed in the Councils of that <hi>Church,</hi> and may be ready to ſay, <hi>That tho' they adore Saints in other manner then the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>do, yet they believe with the</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>that Divine Adoration
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105289:15"/>is due only to God.</hi> When in Diſcourſe with a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> of great Knowledg, in the Controverſal Points of their Religion, I alledged the Superſtition and Inefficacy of their Praying to Saints, in regard they were neither Omnipre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to hear all Prayers, nor Omniſcient to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern between the Sincerity and Hypocriſie of any that Pray'd to them. He gave me no ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Anſwer, but returned upon me an Objection, <hi>That thoſe of the Communion of the</hi> Church of England <hi>preſcribed ſomething that lookt like it, in their daily Devotions, when they exhorted or called upon the Souls and Spirits of juſt Men made Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and</hi> Ananias, Azarias <hi>and</hi> Miſael <hi>in particular to praiſe the Lord.</hi> To which I could not make him any ſatisfactory Reply, without granting more upon the firſt Point than I thought was conſonant to the Scriptures, which I take to be the Directory of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> I write not this in any Caſe as pleading in excuſe, or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving countenance to any Superſtitious or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Practice, but to ſhew how abſtruce ſome terms in the <hi>Teſt</hi> are to be preciſely Interpreted and rightly underſtood, and that becauſe by how much the leſs perfectly any ſolemn Oath or At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation is underſtood by ſuch as take it, by ſo much of leſs weight it will be upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to obſerve it; and if in proceſs of time ſuch a Law, being perpetual, may become very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the general ſcope of it, and in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is ſo now. The ſooner it comes to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, altered or wholly laid aſide, ſo much the better; and if it be well weighed how this Law, and the Law for the firſt <hi>Teſt</hi> alſo intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches upon ſeveral Points of Royal Prerogative, which in other Caſes, both as to Laws of a Religious and of a Civil Nature, has been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore rendred as a reaſon and juſt ground of their repeal. and how theſe Laws have and do ſubject many Perſons to temporal Penalties and Diſabilities as to the enjoyment of Civil Rights for their Conſcientious Diſſent in Religious Opinions from the <hi>Church of England.</hi> It may appear very juſt and reaſonable, that theſe Laws ſhould be again conſidered in the next ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Parliament,</hi> and either Repealed, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo explained and altered, That the Sovereign Prerogative, and the Subjects Civil Rights, may be better provided for then they are by theſe Laws as they now remain.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. If together with the Repeal deſired, the ſubſtance of the <hi>Kings Declaration</hi> be entirely and in the ſame Law of Repeal enacted, which in the firſt place is <hi>to maintain the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Clergy, and all other his Subjects of the</hi> Church of England <hi>in the free exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as by Law Eſtabliſhed, and in the quiet and full enjoyment of all their Poſſeſſions.</hi> All ſuch grand ſubverſions of the preſent order of things Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, and general change of Hands in things of a Civil Nature, as have heretofore happened. upon the Succeſſive <hi>Soveraigns</hi> differing from the Religion Eſtabliſhed in the Raign of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, may not only for the Preſent, but in all future Ages alſo be avoided; and the Mutations which in any gradual courſe are likely to enſue ſuch a Repeal, and proviſion at the ſame time made either in Civil or Religious Concerns, will in all probability be leſs Perceptible, and leſs In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, during this Generation then ever has been experimented in the like Caſe, or can otherwiſe be reaſonably expected upon ſuch a change in the Government as has now hapned, eſpecially if the Severities for the cauſe of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which have been for many Years exerciſed, and the inconſiſtency of theſe Teſt Laws, made in the Reign of a <hi>Proteſtant King,</hi> as to Attendances on the Perſon of the <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and the Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations required as to all Civil and Military Offices upon the Succeſſion of a <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion</hi> to the Throne, be well conſidered.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. A Repeal of ſuch <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> as are before mentioned, may, if his <hi>Majeſty</hi> pleaſe to give his Royal Aſſent, be recompenced by other Proviſions properly neceſſary to prevent future Mutations. In Eſtabliſhing Corporations upon a more ſixt Foundation then they ſtand at preſent, by a previous <hi>Teſt,</hi> of a civil Nature, to be taken by all Perſons therein, and in all other Places and Counties who are otherwiſe qualified to Elect, before they give their Votes in any Election. By Clauſes in the Indentures, before the Elected be returned, and by every Perſon who ſhall be Elected to ſerve in Parliament, or put into any Office or Place of Truſt or Power, in framing Commiſſions for the exerciſe of Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures, and many other things of like Nature which the Wiſdom of a Parliament may readily ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>For a Cloſe, by reflecting upon the two main Points before mentioned, the one claimed by his <hi>Majeſty</hi> as inſeperably annext to, and inherent in his Royal Perſon by the Law of Nature,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105289:15"/>TO HAVE THE BENEFIT OF THE SERVICE OF ALL HIS LOVING SUBJECTS. The other granted by their <hi>Highneſſes,</hi> THAT NO CHRISTIAN OUGHT TO BE ILL USED, BECAUSE HE DIF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FERS FROM THE PULICK AND ESTABLISHED RELIGION. There is one thing more occurs which I ſhall offer to conſideration, which ſeems to me, taken ſingly (if there were no more to be alledged in this caſe) a good reaſon why theſe <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> which require the taking of the <hi>Sacrament Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> ſhould be either in expreſs terms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, or (which is tantamount) by ſome new Law, ſo explained and limitted as that the Penalties and Diſabilites may not be inevitable, but ſome way or other (by and conſiſtent with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of a good Conſcience towards <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King)</hi> be avoided. For as the caſe now ſtands, His <hi>Majeſty</hi> being pleaſed to Nominate, Authorize and Appoint many Perſons who are Diſſenters from the Eſtabliſhed Religion, (and in that regard cannot with a good Conſcience take <hi>Sacraments, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> in the manner they are enjoyned) to execute ſeveral publick Offices, and ſome ſuch Perſons may alſo be Called or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to ſerve in Parliament. If any of them do refuſe to ſerve in any of theſe publick Offices or Places of Truſt, they are by our Laws liable to be very ill uſed by Fines and Impriſonments, and that juſtly too (as is preſumed) becauſe they refuſe to Execute ſuch Offices and Places of Truſt, as are not only Lawful but Neceſſary, and muſt be Executed by them or ſome others: No Man can by our preſent Laws excuſe himſelf (when he is not legally priviledged or exempted) from any Service to which he is lawfully called by his own Default, that is by his not qualifying himſelf according to the Directions of Law for the Execution of thoſe Places, and if he do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and ſerve in thoſe Places, without ſuch a Qualfication (to which he cannot in Conſcience ſubmit) he is obnoxious to as ill uſage for Serving and Acting in thoſe Offices and Places of Truſt as if he refuſed, ſo that until the Law be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe declared, or ſome ſuiteable Proviſion in this caſe made by ſome other Law. Such as are moſt conſciencious and deſirous to diſcharge that reſpective Duty which they ow to <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>King,</hi> and their <hi>Country,</hi> in our preſent Circumſtances are more liable then any others to be very ill uſed; and if this be well conſidered, that the <hi>King</hi> who has the ſole Nomination and Power to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize ſuch Perſons as he pleaſes to ſerve in places of higheſt Judicature and Truſt: And Electors, if they may have their free Choice, as by Law they ought to have, will probably, in many places, chuſe ſuch as are <hi>Diſſenters</hi> to ſerve in Parliament, when his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhall pleaſe to ſend out his Writs for that purpoſe. It ought to be ſhewn, That as the Laws now are, the <hi>King</hi> has no Power to Appoint or Command, and the <hi>Electors</hi> no Power to chuſe ſuch Perſons to ſerve in Offices or Places of Truſt, or otherwiſe, it is requiſit that theſe preſent Laws be Repealed, or ſo far altered and limitted that ſuch as are Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may be ſecured in their Conſciences, Civil Liberties and Properties either for ſerving with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking the <hi>Sacrament Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> or for refuſing to ſerve becauſe they cannot take them; and whoſoever ſhall well weigh the apparent Inconveniences and ill Conſequences that are likely to follow on the one Hand, by any Perſon being permitted to excuſe himſelf from a hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous or chargeable Office or Place of Truſt, upon pretence of Conſcience, and the difficulty of contriving any ſuch Law as ſhall limit the <hi>Kings Prerogative</hi> and the <hi>Subjects Election,</hi> ſo as that the King ſhall not command any of his Subjects to attend his Perſon, ſerve in Parliament, or execute any publick Office or Imployment Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Military, but ſuch only as voluntarily have or will take the <hi>Sacrament, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> and ſo as the Penalty incurred ſhall fall upon the Perſons who Elect any Man to ſerve in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to any ſuch Office, in caſe the Perſon Elected will not Voluntary take them in manner as by Law preſcribed. And if it be conſider'd on the other Hand how juſtifiable and equal it is, and how we may be by other ways ſecured againſt all Hazards, if theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts</hi> be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed. It may appear more eaſie and ſafe to Repeal theſe <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> then to contrive any New Law conſiſtent with the continuance of thoſe Laws in force, which ſhall be effectual to remedy the aforementioned and now unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inconveniences.</p>
            <p>What his Lordſhip ſays, pag. 4, 5. That there is a great difference to be obſerved in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of thoſe of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> where they have the Government, towards <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi>'s, and of the Conduct of the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick's</hi> where they have the Government, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as are of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, and this may be a caution why no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105289:16"/>
               <hi>Proteſtant Governors,</hi> of a <hi>Proteſtant Nation</hi> ſhould voluntarily invite any <hi>Roman Catholick's</hi> to take a ſhare with them in their Government who cannot claim any right in it, but this does not reach our Caſe at all. We are providentially brought under the Government of a <hi>Sovereign Prince</hi> who is of the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion,</hi> And he hath many Subjects, of the ſame Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who by the Laws of Nature claim according to their Quality and Numbers, an equal ſhare with others in the enjoyment of Civil Rights and Priviledges; and under our preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, it is equally as unjuſt &amp; unſafe to preſs for the execution of ſuch <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt them for their Religions ſake, as it would be to preſs for the obſervance of Rules made in a common Caſe, when we fall under ſuch Emergenies as require the ſuperſion of them. Beſides as we have a <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion,</hi> ſo we have alſo a <hi>Soveraign</hi> who in this reſpect differs from and excels all others of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in that His deſires are to ſettle all things on ſuch a Foundation, as may be a laſting ſecurity to all his Subjects, ſo far as Soveraign Power, the wiſdom of a Parliament, ſubjects conſent, and common intereſt of the whole can provide; that none of them may ſuffer any dammage in their civil Rights, for the ſake of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that all civil Intereſts, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their different opinions in Religion, may be united in the common defence and Security of his Majeſties, Kingdoms; a thing moſt deſirable in its ſelf, and moſt conducible to the Safety, Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and Honour of the Nation, Other Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>States</hi> may well be jealous of, and underhand indeavour what they can to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſuch a Settlement but in contemplation that their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> are in a poſſibility of ſuceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Throne,</hi> I ſee no reaſon why it ſhould not be eſteemed their Intereſt to promote the ſettlement of his <hi>Majeſties Three Kingdomes</hi> on ſuth a Foundation of Peace and Union as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by his Royal and Gracious <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if none of theſe things which I have written can prevail with his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> to move their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> to give their Conſent and Aſſiſtance upon ſuch due terms of caution, as are offered by his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to the repeal of theſe <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts,</hi> which ſtand in the way of ſuch a peaceable and laſting Settlement, as is propoſed and deſired, yet I hope it may prevail with him ſo to repreſent to their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> ſuch of the Diſſenters as in their reſpective Stations, indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the accompliſhment thereof, as that their <hi>Highneſſes</hi> may not be offended thereat, Becauſe what they have done and ſhall do herein. IS OUT OF GRATITUDE AND DU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY TO HIS MAJESTY, OBEDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCE TO THE GENERAL LAWS BOTH OF NATURAL AND RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEALED RELIGION, AND LOVE TO THE PRINCIPLES AND PROSPERITY OF THE REFORM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED RELIGION. <hi>Which forbids every Man to do that to another, which he would not have done to himſelf, and commands every Man to do his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent duty to God in the firſt place, and to his preſent Soveraign in the next place;</hi> leaving the ſucceſs and future events of their ſo doing to the Wiſe and Gracious diſpoſal of God, who judgeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Gods, ſitteth upon the Floods as King for ever, does Rule, and Will over-Rule all things as for his own Glory, ſo alſo for the good of them that ſear him, and knows how to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Godly out of Tamptations: Into whoſe Hands it is better to commit the keeping of our Souls in well-doing, with ſuch hazards as attend the outward Man, then for the preſervation of the outward Man, to ſtrain any Religious Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in reference to civil Concerns in any ſuch manner or meaſure as is inconſiſtent with the general Laws of Religion and Nature, for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever makes uſe of any ſuch method to preſerve his civil Concerns, or defend or propagate his Religion, it may be ſuſpected he is either wrong in his Opinion, or takes a wrong courſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105289:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
